all right i think you're alive now
okay thank you and hello everybody do a
new
wasabi research experience a meeting
and this time we have a special guest
he is jako mosuko i think he doesn't
need
further presentation so
we want to talk about a few things
that i i personally think are very
important like
well privacy uh as a tool probably
and freedom from the optics of the
austrian economics and
you know free stuff i mean
we can talk about whatever we want and
and take the opportunity to to ask
giacomo whatever we want okay jacob
welcome thank you honored to be here
you misgendered me with my with the
problem
presenting me but i will forgive you for
now so
we can we can start okay
i'm sorry but how do you to self i'll
identify
today uh today i have to check i have a
list of
identification i'm not sure myself i
will check the list later but we can go
on in the meantime
okay perfect okay well
just to start and i would like to know
what your opinion about
then the
progress if you if you think there is
any
in privacy in bitcoin development
and what have you seen as
promising technology
how what effect do you believe if
if any it can happen in our society
yeah so we we were already chatting a
little bit about these topics and my
my main takeaway will be first uh
privacy in the physical realm in the mid
space
uh it's very very difficult every every
every day which is passing is more deep
it's going to be more difficult
2020 was incredible from the point of
view of restriction
of people crossing borders and even
in some countries like italy people just
walking by the street
they get stopped and asked where they
are going and why
and and and who gave them the permission
so the situation in the physical realm
in the mid space is basically very very
dire
which is opening interesting opportunity
uh following the old cypherpunk idea
in the digital realm the whole
cypherpunk idea was basically that
even if you cannot really stop people
from harassing you
and and stalking you and tracking you
and spying on you
on the physical realm especially after
technological development made
made cheaper to try to uh to do mass
surveillance
uh you can still using encryption and
strong cryptography and
um and technological tools in general
you can still
counter counter uh this tendency and
and fight in the digital realm in the
cyber space uh
and this is basically i think this kind
of
scenario was less uh understood and less
felt even by bitcoiners just a few years
ago
because there was a general sentiment
and even uh
mid-space see the situation was going to
be better like
many people were were joining this kind
of nomadic way of life where just move
around the world without many
restrictions you are nomadic so
even if some situation is is bad you
just do
uh jurisdictional arbitrage and you move
elsewhere and you are better off
right now in the last two years i think
situation is
is changing and uh and so more and more
people
are getting interested in privacy
uh in the digital realm as opposed to
the to the other
situation uh the idea is that the
the problem with privacy is that you
realize you need it when it's too late
only when people will use the
information about you in order to
punish you because you said something
wrong because you
you purchased something that is uh that
is taboo because you
you sponsored somebody that you were
supposed and you were not supposed to
sponsor
so the the the you appreciate privacy
when it's too late
but now it is too late because many
people are starting to suffer from
consequences of surveillance so now i
think that
people that there is more awareness
about privacy the more
the more governments and society as well
uh try to censor and and deanonymize and
track and stalk and spy
the more people actually feel the the
importance of the tools to avoid that
and uh for example uh today
is the uh is what we elected as the
coinjoin day so it's very appropriate to
be
in this chat with with one of the main
coin join implementations
uh people from a very important
implementation because
it is also another sign of awareness if
you think about
coin join as a technique uh a few years
ago
nobody would i mean probably let's
imagine i don't know
uh march or april of 2014
uh i guess that probably 10 to 50 people
knew what conjoined was at all uh
reading the post of
gregory marshall probably only the
people answering to gregory maxwell on
bitcoin talk
and maybe a few developers of dark
wallet implementation with stealth
address and stuff like that
and the people working on on uh joint
market
uh implementation so basically watch
swing and
belcher and so on but i i guess nobody
else knew
that exactly what conjer was and now we
also have a day which is uh i mean is
not
a huge uh popularity success because a
few people are celebrating yet
uh but it's still some funny things that
we do uh it was chosen today because uh
today is the birthday of satoshi
nakamoto in his uh
in his uh online forms it is also a very
symbolic day because it is the date of
the
gold confiscation in the usa so it is
the day in which
franklin dan roosevelt a president in a
in a advanced liberal democracy as you
may call it so the united states of
america
not 500 years ago but just a few decades
ago basically decided to single-handedly
confiscate
all the gold possessed by american
citizens
so not even confiscating from the jews
or the
gypsies or the communists or the enemies
or the immigrants
or the the women or whatever kind of
minority
could be more weak they just confiscated
every single
uh well every single american citizen
they were able
to physically find and confiscate of
course it was especially
easy to confiscate paper gold inside
bank accounts
but they also went for physical goals in
a few occasions
with with actual uh state police
enforcement uh blitz to take
gold from people so this date is very
important because it reminds you that
uh that even if you
are in a in a honeymoon phase in which
government seems not really interested
into attacking bitcoin
and maybe they even seem sympathetic or
tolerant
or neutral when [__] hits the fan
hard then everything can change and can
change pretty fast
from from a situation where gold work
was
basically the the main store of value
for regular people
to a situation where gold was actively
confiscated by policemen
in the united states of america a few
decades ago so
uh this is a very symbolic day to think
about
uh the fact that bitcoin may not always
be
treated uh as something neutral
especially if the price go up
and numbers go up and and the numbers of
the dollar
purchasing power keep keep going down
then
the situation may become problematic so
uh in this day it is important not just
to uh to
to improve security so of course to to
to be uh of course uh to self-custody
the keys
the bitcoin keys to improve uh situation
strategies of multi-sig uh key
distribution
plausible deniability and stuff like
that but it's also important to protect
privacy
because uh it's very difficult to
protect yourself from
a very powerful attacker if the attacker
knows everything about
what how much do you have where do you
have it which addresses
when you move them uh when do you move
them
usually where do you spend what do you
buy uh if if the attacker has
all these information about you he will
have a
very unfair advantage over you it would
be
very difficult i think as uh let's think
as an example to the
the ledger league situation i think
that's very important if you compare
with bitcoin privacy
uh ledger uh had a leak
of a database a commercial database of
uh people buying the
the nano s stuff and uh and so
the situation was basically pretty
simple a list of names
with the physical address for shipping
the wallet
and an email and sometimes the telephone
number
and that's all and the information that
probably these people
had a few bitcoins or a few [__] coins
because if
they if they have if they if they bother
to spend money for another wallet
probably they own some bitcoin or [__]
coin so
this was sufficient for uh scammers and
and and fraudsters and attackers
everywhere to
to target these people uh using the list
so they started first with phishing
attacks
so just using the telephone number to
say hey put here your seat because
we we are updating the firmware so you
need to put this uh
your seed inside this link and many many
people fall for it
but also there have been reported some
some physical attacks
uh or some attempts of extortions like
emails like
i know you have bitcoin so give me
uh bitcoin here otherwise i will start
to uh
to show up at your door and to attack
your family and stuff like that
of course if you think about uh this
this kind of problem
uh coming out from a simple list of name
telephone numbers and and address
effects of shipping
and possibly the fact that you do have
another wallet
imagine what you could have could have
if you have a list
of names addressed with proof of
constant residency and
a copy of a valid document and then the
amount of bitcoin that you purchased
and the exact date of purchase and
exactly address of withdrawal
and everything you did before and after
from your address
withdrawal address and before your
deposit
you take so so if you have all these the
amount
of not only extortion or blackmail
but even just social engineering like
the the the
the easiness to convince you that i'm a
legit
uh hardware wallet operator asking you
to uh
to upgrade your firmware uh and any kind
of at or or just
uh the facility that i have to contact
your relatives
um telling information about you your
picture
or to go on other services using your uh
passport information so the kyc list
is a super dangerous list and it's uh
it's dangerous in general
even if you just uh if you just every
time you buy bitcoin with kyc you're
you're basically
risking a lot but even if you
risk a lot it's even more risky if after
buying with kyc
you will basically keep the truck the
on-chain truck
connecting your identity with your
bitcoins with all the following
movements
after the purchase so that's very very
very uh
bad so for this reason uh the the the
the date of uh april the the fifth
was basically uh connected
with coinjoin i think it was responding
to trace mayor
just before he revealed the reason for
uh for
his fud on coinjoin he spent a few
months
uh feuding um conjoined like
oh you should not go enjoying otherwise
you may mix money with uh
syrian terrorists and get in trouble
which is of course nonsense for reason
that
we may elaborate later on but then he he
revealed the reason for that
fed uh because he was launching his own
privacy
scam coin so he had to promote the scam
coin by
uh downplaying the importance of uh coin
joining on on the actual bitcoin
uh so that was the day chosen to promote
but anyway more in general this is about
coin joints so we can discuss
wasabi other implementation uh but
more in general think about tor for
example
uh we have a lot of people now running
nodes
not just with uh not just by installing
a bitcoin core on their computer
but especially buying purchasing a small
raspberry pi
and installing a pre pre
uh pre-packed uh pre-packaged uh
turnkey solutions like uh
raspberry blitz or uh node my node
or ambrell or s9 labs
embassy or uh or or you buy from noodle
the the pre pre-built machine or stuff
like that
there was kaza now is out of production
but there was that as well
or you can just build your your node
using guides
like the raspberry bolt guide or stuff
like that
all these solutions they they used to to
use uh
just a clear net ip but since
they they also implement the lightning
and since lightning is pretty
problematic if you show up your your
home ip everywhere
all these solutions are basically now
offering tor
as default to connect to you to your
node and to expose
the the lightning version of your node
but of course
when you start to use store for
lightning then you basically use it also
for broadcasting on chain transactions
and stuff like that so people using
wazabi are already using
tor people using this kind of complex
node
packages are using tor of course tor
itself
is not perfect is a semi centralized
it's not completely decentralized and
the team
controlling tor i think there are a few
reasons to be uh to be very adversarial
in thinking about this team right now
and they may be better alternative in
the future like uh
ip3 i mean there may be alternatives but
right now tor is basically
the the best stuff we have in production
already
to do to preserve privacy online and
it's basically getting everywhere
not just for privacy this is also very
important the another reason
that taurus is being used is that
managing
static ips is is a is painful is very
annoying especially for non-experienced
users so people will basically use store
even just to have static
static address to connect to which is
very very cool
of course there's still there's still a
lot of stuff to do for example
assume that you want to open a shop and
you want to be paid in bitcoin and
lightning so you would probably use a
btc
server or something like that and btcp
server of course cannot
expose directly uh your tor
uh tor page onion page because otherwise
people connecting on clearnet will not
be able to buy stuff from you
so it's there is a lot of there is a lot
of stuff to do uh i i'm very optimistic
about the things that we will see in the
future
tap root is is coming fast and taproot
is
a huge privacy improvement because
basically you will have
uh of light and network channels
completely indistinguishable from for a
single transaction single on
chain transaction and you will also have
multi-sig
secure call storage operation
indistinguishable from
normal uh single seek transaction you
will reduce the fingertip of the wallet
so that's also very very nice
uh so temperature is cool what i
especially think
will be revolutionary for bitcoin would
be a combination
between uh cross input uh cross input
uh signature aggregation and a high
ion chain fee environment because right
now let's be
honest uh coin joining is is the best
practice for security
but is in trade-off with saving money
because
it's expensive especially with high fees
while
uh after you have a single uh
signature aggregation cross-input coin
joining will save you money
so people will be incentivized to do
conjoined just to save money
on transaction in an environment with
very high fees so there is a lot of
stuff going on
and yeah probably the answer was too
long
i attached it to many points so i would
stop here
one more question and one only one
question per participant
okay but okay listen
yeah we have been discussing about
basically
things that can happen in the in the
bitcoin ecosystem and
technology how technology can can evolve
to make this
better and also it seems we more or less
agree that
in the the digital world or
cyber space things are looking good
but if we cannot do anything to improve
the situation in the real world that's a
defeat
because i mean i'm pretty sure this has
this technology and no no bitcoin is
not bitcoin only all this technology
store for example and
that you mentioned bitcoin another
should make a big impact
on on the on the real world
and i'm not so sure if that is something
that
is going to happen really but so
i'm the pessimist here i don't know
what's your opinion
if you have an opinion
uh jim i mean you're i think you're
right to be pessimistic about uh
about a physical world uh of course
the the cypherpunk ideal is to is that
even if you are living in a state of
slavery
uh in the physical world as long as
which we actually are basically almost
everywhere
if you do have uh at least
uh three things which is uh
a way to look at your screen without
people
spying on you directly which is
something that people for example in
jail they don't have it
and we can assume that we in our home we
still have it
for now so you you have the you can
interact with the computer
then you have the second assumption
which you can access
to general computing devices which is
not absolutely to be taken for granted
for example
right now most of the people on this
planet use the mobile phones as
computers
and general computational mobile phones
is still possible basically especially
in
android but it's it's very it's very
easy to get
like main cell phone producers basically
benny
starting to actively uh to make
impossible
to run general purpose software on the
phones or
already now it's very difficult to find
stuff on app stores
and we may have we already had a ban
of any kind of bitcoin tool from app
stores we are lucky that right now
we are in a phase in which uh bitcoin
stuff
are not banned from app stores but it's
not 70 to be taken for granted
so the second assumption is you can
access to a general purpose computer
which is not obvious the first
assumption is you can access
3d to the internet which of course
is not really the case in china and and
and elsewhere but still many people are
going to use
vpn and there are satellites and they
are mesh network is not
a solvent problem but i think that if
you have these three
if you can make these three assumptions
then
you you can at least do basically one
thing
which is preserving free speech and even
if you are not
dreaming that you cannot move walk work
exchange act
kiss people drink alcohol smoke
tobacco or eat steaks
or do whatever you want if you can speak
with other people
you can organize you can basically do
everything which is
information exchange and information
organization which is already a big deal
because then you can start to organize a
counter-attack you can start to organize
a defense
you can start to organize bubbles of
liberty
within slavery you can basically
when you have access to free information
you can
basically do stuff even in the physical
work at least
organizing it with other people with
things like you
so if you don't have that you are a
complete slave if you have that
you you can still follow for example now
we can find other
fellow bitcoiners we can rent a huge
resort somewhere
for a few months and when we are there
we can basically do what
literally whatever the hell we want with
very low probability to be
uh to be bothered by by
cops or or i don't know mafia henchmen
or
narcos or whatever uh if the security is
good if
the planning is good uh it's there is a
an old saying by by antonopoulos
which is uh uh free speech is i mean the
internet enables free speech
and uh basically bitcoin makes money
part of speech because now you have a
digital version of money
and so basically now as long as you have
free speech on the internet you also
have
money with bitcoin and i could add
that stuff like 3d printed guns may
also play the same role now you can
actually
you can trade guns with the same
as part of free speech as long as i can
distribute
uh 3d printing uh instructions for
for uh distributed defense uh projects
and and guns and stuff like that
i may have access to the i mean it's not
that
that simple because you still need
access to uh ammunition
and but there are a few projects to 3d
print a monitor as well so
i i i don't so i don't think that
internet inform information uh
freedom is uh sufficient
to be free but it's certainly necessary
to be free
at scale in this age so if you don't
have that
you have nothing if you have that if you
have a
internet anonymity internet privacy you
can build
uh economics freedom on top of that with
bitcoin
and you can basically uh
print guns um basically i think i mean
it's
better than than nothing of course there
are still few things missing like
uh transportation travel uh that's very
very hard especially now
but still uh so let's let's consider
this uh
i have to move to uh bahamas in
next month and now i cannot touch the
united states because i cannot enter
for uh for uh coronage restrictions but
uh i have a friend who suggested me
to to to basically rent a private jet
and to fill it and the price would come
down to about
4 000 euro for me which is too much for
me right now i would probably not do it
but if i think about uh
numbers going up in bitcoin a lot that
may become an option for for many kind
of uh
of initiatives so you see it's all
connected uh
the internet enables bitcoin bitcoin is
is money it's good money it's harmony
when you have harmony you are better off
even from your
purchasing power uh point of view and
when you are purchasing power
you can buy freedom by spending more
and by and by uh purchasing
uh freedom tools like private jet
basically
uh so it's so connected i'm not saying
that the situation is good
but uh i'm saying that the battle for
uh cyberspace freedom is probably
the main battle we we can still win and
we have to win and then there will be uh
fullbacks
positive uh feedbacks also on
on the physical uh freedom
around you
is very important uh so and physical
surveillance resistance
like what do you think are some suitable
defense strategies
against active surveillance measures in
meat space
well a nice thing about uh about uh uh
this mosque situation is that uh for
example
in italy there are a few atms by bitcoin
atms by the company
uh shitcoins.com which has a very ironic
name they they also sell [__] coins but
they also sell bitcoin
and they're basically kyc free which is
completely legal in italy
but they just don't care and they just
keep them
working as long as cops will not tear
them down
they just work they basically uh they
plan
for the legal risk uh in a smart way in
a
kind of conservative way and they just
operate
i i mean since we're talking in english
and i don't think any kind of italian
government parasite will
i will we'll be listening right now i
can just uh
say it freely i think they are basically
managing uh
the or not themselves maybe maybe
they're their hosts
that are hosting this machine but anyway
they still have cameras because even if
they are not
making kyc control so you don't have to
put any kind of the document
they have cameras which are activated
because if they also deactivated cameras
like they do
in switzerland for example where you
don't have a kyc obligation
under uh i think three thousand francs
or something so if you go in zurich
and you and withdrawal from a bitcoin
atm you
or your deposit you don't see cameras
often
they are basically obscured some some of
them if you go in italy you see cameras
but now you i mean if you are very very
scared of viruses
uh maybe when you buy bitcoin you want
to
have masks and protective glasses and i
mean
still not perfect because they are they
are basically
uh they can even just
track you from the way you walk another
kind of
more general biometrics
biometrics but still masks
facial recognition is already very
difficult if people started to get
to get must on a lot i usually don't
like to do that a lot
but i do that a lot when i'm close to
bitcoin atms
and and then you basically you have to
to to solve the problem of travel uh if
you can solve like moving
via land via car crossing borders with
low level of control is pretty easy of
course there
are that there is complete surveillance
of the borders
especially for microscopic operations if
you start to
uh well let me give you another example
uh getting back to private jets i asked
to this friend what who is often moving
with private jets
all the time he's pretty he was already
pretty rich before bitcoin
and what kind of control is he subjected
to
and he said nothing literally nothing he
enters the private terminal with
the capitan that he booked for from the
company and it just goes up
and there is a policeman there usually
but it doesn't get checked
for uh for anything including weapons or
or drugs or anything
of course you cannot use that at scale
as a microscopic way to move illegal
stuff
across you you cannot use that
extensively as a way to
really uh break the rules otherwise you
will just
you will just attract a new attention
and the game will be over
but if you just do that to smuggle
yourself uh
i think that's pretty effective of
course it's very very expensive but
again uh the point about bitcoin is that
usually freedom fighters tend to be uh
very committed and smart but also very
poor
uh bitcoin freedom fighters
for the first time in a in a long time
could be a case of very committed
ideologically committed
and and rigorous people with a
very strong felt uh cause
which are also going to become pretty
rich
which can create interesting and
unpredicted
uh force balances let's say
so private citadels and private travel
in between citadels
that's something that i would just find
it going on
yep i will not uh go on a route of we
are actually discussing that with a lot
of people
i would personally not go on a route of
of any kind of
overt like nothing like liberland you
know or
or israel de la rosa where you just
write to the on
uh or the systeming institute of peter
tl
where you just tell the world that
you're going to exit
the the jurisdiction of nation states uh
you don't
but maybe just very simple
touristic operations like touristic
resorts
with not no political statement at all
outside
but happened to be run by fellow
like-minded bitcoiners that
agreed to give you a lot of technical
privacy inside and a lot of
a lot of arbitrage uh about rules of uh
where to move how to move and how to
track the way you move
and stuff like that of course uh
touristic resource with
private jets is a pretty interesting
setup uh i guess boats
and navigation by the sea can also offer
even more
resistance to surveillance if you need
it uh
yeah we have to basically i think we
have to copy
uh what narcos are doing
okay someone else guys any question
i was just wondering how many spots do
you have on that private jet
in this specific case it was basically
spots but but i'm not taking the deal
because it's too expensive for me but it
was at 18 spots from milan to
bahamas and um and
the total cost was little short of 80
so uh distribute two ways so
distributing was
not that bad but still too much for me
right now
especially for the fact that of course i
don't have bitcoin i i've lost
everything in a very unfortunate boating
accident so
that's why i cannot afford it but it was
interesting just to
enter in the in the set of ideas
hmm yeah that is interesting to just
just to know about these like prices and
that this is an actual option never came
to my mind
but yeah i was also just wondering like
uh i don't know you probably read this
uh book
sovereign individual uh giacomo and
there was like this
this phrase that uh it's gonna be
interesting to see whenever
like the governments will start to clamp
down on their citizens
uh to like restrict them even more and
more uh
like they were saying that you know
probably the only ones who are gonna
stay put
is the the like the foolish ones
and the most nationalist ones but this
means that we will kind of like be
on like running and you know we have to
escape them
uh what do you think about this like is
that a good strategy or is it just
better to stand
up and fight already
uh i so i yes i i i've read
the silver individual even pre-bitcoin
and it was one of the cases
of basically pretty much prediction of
bitcoin
uh so it was a very uh a very
uh insightful book and a very
uh prophetic book in a way the other
notable cases are milton friedman
predicting bitcoin or
or uh freddie phonayak predicting
bitcoin
and you can find the videos of both but
other case was the the silver individual
that was the the part about money
basically uh describing a few features
of
something which is pretty close to what
what bitcoin is i think that in a way
the sovereign individual was a little
bit too much optimistic
because it was written in a situation
where
the the degree of government
intervention on the specific territories
was becoming worse but the degree of
easiness to move across border was
becoming
way better and was continuously becoming
better
is financially becoming better less
expensive
less friction full uh less problematic
for more and more people
uh it was not completely unrealistic
because
the the way the book is is uh is making
his prediction is basically
i'm oversimplifying here but it's
basically predicting
a a the coupling in
in classes where there is basically the
the slave class which will be basically
bound to nation states with the worst
worse and worse condition and less and
less freedom and on the other hand
this kind of class let's call it in this
marxist way of several individuals able
to move and to
do uh arbitrage and to basically profit
from arbitrage and take the best of of
everything
and governments competing to attract
these people etc
so it was it was not too much optimistic
because
already back then the the situation of
progressive freedom was
intended for for a selected fuse
in a way not not really for everybody
not for the average joe
but uh i i reading it back again
uh last year a few chapters of that book
i found it now uh over optimistic about
especially travel situation of course
you cannot predict everything
but uh it was you can feel the
perception that
freedom of movement across the world for
the new generations is basically
irreversible
which was not at all as we have seen
right now i mean people in uk they
cannot even leave
the the state which is exactly uh
like the situation in east germany uh
it's incredible
of course it's all uh temporary
because uh you know uh government
temporary restrictions are always very
very temporary
but uh but still incredible to think
about
but in other way so it was over
optimistic
but another way i still think that's the
way uh of course it's it will just be
harder than predicted in that book
but uh i think that book is a very good
uh
i mean that book was was depicting a
very peaceful transition
between uh between uh the nation-state
pardim
and the sovereign individual networks of
individuals paradigm
uh it was very peaceful in a way uh
just like a natural evolution driven by
competition
of jurisdictions uh the the the actual
situation we are seeing will probably be
less peaceful
it will be closer to a collapse so like
uh you know the the
like the roman empire collapse or
something like that i get i i don't
think that the fiat ward
can get better before it gets
way worse and finally collapses uh
it it's just too much uh
uh beyond any kind of uh
possibility of repair reparation
you know something that i that i that
i've seen these days
is well i was sharing here that
um yesterday in a local
newspaper uh a
journalist was complaining that there
were people
working with computers i mean
programmers
working for companies in other countries
and they were paid in bitcoins or
in dollars but not in the local banks
but in
in banks in in other countries mostly in
the u.s in the united states
and well it was uh
like a drama right because that you know
those
workers that don't love the the country
enough
to to
to bring the money so the government can
take it right
and and how to say this
and give just a send to everybody
um and this same thing was
happening last month in spain
where there was a huge problem because
most of the youtubers are leaving the
country as well as the poker players and
other
digital guys let's say
and the the controversial was that
if that people should be allowed to
leave the country
that is the level of craziness that
we are seeing now so the idea that
given you are productive and you are
um you live or you pass most of your
time
in the in the virtual world
yes there are countries that probably uh
good luck to have you but the state
your state don't want to let you leave
and it will be
i think that that the problem that we
will see
more often i don't know if someone will
share this
yeah actually i did think of that
because it seems like
these restrictions for moving out seems
to like
be popping up already and that's why i
kind of like
i'm wondering if it's an actually like
better strategy to
just move the [__] out when it's
still possible or to actually stay put
and try to fight
in yeah like wherever you are already
question is where you can move to
yeah exactly the the real question is
where because if there was
like if there is something like the cold
war and you are in east germany and
there is west germany and it's very
clear
which the distinction is then if you can
escape before they close the wall
then you escape if you are like my my
grandparents
they were in italy and if a few
relatives
that were not just lucky but also smart
enough
to move to switzerland before uh
mussolini's
entered in the in the conflict they were
smart enough to
to to basically to save themselves from
the
most of the consequences of later on but
in these cases you have a clear
distinction of two parts of the world
for example in world war ii you have
belligerent countries or probably
soon belligerent countries like italy
and you have neutral countries like
switzerland
so it's clear what kind of trade-off you
have you have to go
and what is the direction of the
immigration in case of the cold war you
have the berlin wall
and you have to cross the banning ward
to go to go west basically
because you have communism and you have
a woman you have
honest communists on the east and you
have the soft kind of
us-based communist uh communist man
there on the right
so on the on the west so you have to
move there uh right now
where do you move exactly i mean if you
compare for example
let's uh as a libert libertarian
uh of course i have always uh take
a look to freedom indexes and stuff like
that
so what are the what are the freeze
countries
and of course there there is usually
hong kong
on top since uh two years ago now hong
kong is basically china so the most
dystopian dictatorship on this planet
and uh then second place you have
switzerland which
is right now basically uh
switzerland is is a police state too uh
two weeks ago i was told to got out of
my private office because the policemen
were starting to make sure
that people were not staying in the
office after after
twenty after nine pm because this is
already a rule that
the that the chino was in the italian
switzerland state
was already implementing in theory since
many years in order to
prevent abuse on workers so
you cannot do uh over war over work
without
some kind of union
regulation but then after uh
the the virus uh hysteria
now these rules are basically being
implemented more because
over over time is forbidden and so
you have policemen going around in
lugano to look for people inside
offices their own offices at 9pm so this
is switzerland
the place that my grandparents were
where were escaping to
in uh in a few decades ago
and in switzerland restaurants all
restaurants which are not hotels
are closed uh country-wise
without without distinction between any
kind of
usually everything in switzerland is
local based so
you have different tax rates on
different towns different
regulations different financial
regulation you have competition
between across towns and across cantons
and
in this case in november a single
addict from bern from the center came to
lock down all the restaurants
and bar and cafes in all the country all
the confederation
without any kind of local distinction
since november without exception
of course with the exception of hotels
because if you are sleeping inside the
hotel
you can still have lunch and dinner so
of course
every person that can that can afford it
is booking hotel rooms in their own
cities
so they can show up have dinner and then
they just pay for the hotel room
and they don't go into the room because
they don't they just they maybe
they just leave across the corner they
just go out and they go home
after having dinner so i it's super
difficult to find a hotel room in lugano
for example
uh it's i usually stay in hotel when i'm
when i'm far from home and it's super
difficult to do that because right now
of course
when you create this kind of situation
you you create also a lot of
of distortion so this is just to say
that this is switzerland the second
most free place in the world and if you
look at
about places where and then you have
uk forbidding people from from going
abroad
basically basically
it's incredible for beating people to
leave the country
uh uk so uh the uk was not traditionally
a super
hard communist dictatorship it was
considered a part
of the relatively free or kind of free
places and even even like tropical
paradises like
panama in parliament when i was in
panama in 2007
uh it was incredible i was discussing
with the lawyer there and we were
discussing like
home addresses and and somebody was
asking
uh how do the government knows where i
am if there is no
a compulsory home address in the
documents and and
the lawyer answer why should the
government know where you are i mean
the worst case scenario they will just
call you with with
or write you an email and you will show
up in a government office if they need
but there's no reason the government
should even know where you live which
was
i mean this is paradise right now panama
was under a super street
uh kind of of restriction so
so the question becomes where do you
move if you follow a 2019
freedom index you will be completely
misled
right now and the the places where where
the the currency situation is not
went that far are not very good places
where you are very much free
like belarus didn't implement one single
restriction
but belarus is belarus is [__] i mean
lukashenko is not really the place you
go to have freedom
and uh i mean norway uh sorry sweden
sweden
they did uh implement less restrictions
than other places way less
but still sweden is like a super
socialist country where you
you don't have free speech for most
situation where you
you pay a lot of taxes when you you you
don't have freedom of
contract and freedom of exchange with
other people
uh japan is is doing pretty well but
it's just
it is japan it's not really a very free
society so
uh the the problem is maybe
to move now until you can is better
but assuming you know where to and i
frankly
don't know it right now
yeah good points i think that it would
be already
like so much better to live in a place
where
your fellow people around you are like
skeptical and maybe not so happy about
what is going on and all the
restrictions considering like
the opposite where in some places
there's like
you are the weirdo who isn't who is
opposing all these restrictions and
everyone around you
this is a very good point more than move
to some places
uh gather together with like-minded
people
which can be done uh already in the
digital world
like i'm i'm starting to select my
social networks
more harshly more uh i'm
way more selective right now because i
don't want people snitching on me
uh so yeah i'm kind of a public figure
so
people know what i think but maybe not
not everybody know
where i am exactly when as they did
a few years ago where i was a little
less uh
preoccupated with that so selecting
social networks online but also
especially
offline if you are in if you are close
to people
i mean let's assume you are you are a
jew
in in during world war two if you have
places to hide
you are basically better off even to get
out of the country before
things get very very bad in in the late
30s
so it's important to have social
networks around you that can
help you that can actually understand
your point and are not going to actually
call the cops on you
and stuff like that so i agree uh
gathering
in communities of like-minded people is
probably something
that we have to start to do now uh not
sure where so i think that the the
better
thing for now is decentralization again
uh
many many places like i know that
francis puyola
has a place somewhere in
south america and i know that uh
kevin locke is building a small
community in other islands
i know that uh scifidian is thinking
about the community in jordan
i know that uh i mean a lot of
bitcoiners are building small
communities in a lot of places
in august there will be this conference
in mexico where a lot of people are
basically
gathering around a few spots
among like-minded people in europe
i have no clue but i guess that
we may find some kind of concentration
of sane individuals
but it's not clear where
who really wants this
this dystopia and for example
in my country if i go out without a mask
the police is not going to to say
anything at all
but people is going it's going to attack
and that's the worst part right i know
you know
i don't know how they do it they have
they have come convinced
ah i don't know how to say this but it
is
hopeless in some way for me that's why
i'm so
pessimistic yeah what
helps me to uh to remain
uh like quiet and uh
generally positive is to think uh
about this uh situation of uh
of uh mass hysteria in a historical
perspective
uh it's incredible that apparently
normal people
are are basically are basically uh
letting go any residual relic
of uh common sense and
and the logics so it's scary to see
uh but if you think about that
historically
you i mean human human
beings have done literally every kind of
crazy [__]
in this sense think about like you have
the aztec
empire these are aztec guys they were
pretty cool they they invented the zero
they they had a good astronomy they
built a very nice pyramids
and then for basically 50 years
they were scared that the sun was going
to run off of fuel
and the only way to uh to basically uh
stop him from shutting down was to kill
around 200 400 people every day to
extract their heart from their their
chest
and to kill children a lot of children
and sometimes to torture
children before killing them and it was
not like one crazy guy like one
i don't know one serial killer it was
basically everybody
apparently norman people of course
guided by by
the by a network
a group of of priests and of
shamans and of sages uh
the doctors basically they were setting
the doctrine
but then everybody else your neighbor
your
your relative was giving you up for
taking the heart out of your chest and
torturing your children
because the sun was going to shut down
so these people really existed in this
in this world it's not science fiction
it's not a fantasy
tale it's something something which
happened
so uh on one side this can be very scary
because we know the people is capable of
that
on the other side thinking that this
only applied
to other ages or other places was
super naive on our part i mean if this
kind of dynamics
can happen to to if you can have
people i mean people's niching of other
people
in order to have them killed because of
their uh
descent in germany in the 30s it was
germany in the 30s
it was not even mexico in in
in the 16th century it was a few decades
ago in europe
and they were basically murdering uh
hundreds of thousands of people
with neighbors snitching on them and you
have in
the us you had concentration camps for
japanese people
and this is basically happening always
so on one side put putting this in
perspective
this is not the first time that
everybody is going completely crazy
and dangerous uh this is probably not
the last time
and in comparison to aztecs this is not
even the most gruesome
uh version of what you can have so we
can
just have i mean we can we have to keep
cool
and and uh and just
find counter attacks and find
and create i mean let's stay
cool-minded let's stay cold-blooded
and let's say uh do not
uh do not get into some kind of cosmic
depression yeah
people are completely crazy not the
first time which this happens
and uh probably not the last and this
time we have a weapon
that uh was not known to man the other
times around
which is uh bitcoin so and everything
would that can be
associated with it and can flourish
around it so
i mean it's it's okay at the end this is
the kind of time we have to deal with
and there are things to do and and and
fights to
to fight
perfect okay shinobi welcome
hola
hola okay um
guys anyone else and by the way can
someone um
host the rest of the meeting because now
i'm
it's hard for me to hold the meeting
if we can just say a few words uh
the thing as you mentioned here like
getting together as a community and
group of people
finding like-minded it's super important
and i think
doing it only digitally won't be enough
especially i mean
i've been having a home office for more
than a year and i'm getting
fairly insane here but i'm able
to to drive up to liberstad where this
is close to where i live
which is a project to establish like a
private city in norway
and while uh we're not that many people
yet it's
super fantastic being able to go up
there and just meet
like-minded people who obviously have
their own
like individual ideas and thoughts about
things but you can trust that
person and you know they they won't run
to the government and tell something and
you know that they have
the same basis of understanding bitcoin
and uh anarcho-capitalism and freedom so
that's uh it's very valuable i think
so we need to build communities around
the world
yeah what i see is that we have to find
the right scale for this
because a too big scale will fail
because basically you will create a
single point of failure
uh that can be a good like a bad single
point of failure like
the government just bombs us because we
are in all the same place
or a good single point of failure like
we all go to new hampshire
then we make taxes very low and
work regulation very loose and so we
have a lot of economic growth
and then a lot of socialists will move
here from from new jersey
and from michigan and from everywhere
and and this will become
a a communist head whole again because
we we succeeded too much
so we have problem of failure uh when
you have centralization
too many people the the idea of the
libertarian paradise
i think it's very dangerous because it's
basically a single point of failure but
also as you say in your message before
the idea of the single individual
moving around alone with his family
without any kind of network of support
around
it's it's a super risky from a
logistical point of view
and super demanding from a psychological
point of view so i think we have to find
the right scale
i'm not opposed to stuff like liberstad
but i think it's even
in a way too big i think it's better to
have smaller
stuff with uh i mean if something
bad happens to liberstad in norway
it's very difficult to move that
community away if something bad happens
to a small citadel-like
resort in norway you just move to uh
to i don't know to a community gated
community in
austin where a lot of bitcoiners are or
in miami
or in or in bahamas or or whatever
and maybe not even in a single point
maybe uh since we all have different
needs like uh maybe my wife doesn't
doesn't like tropical climates and
so everybody has it so my point
is too concentrated is probably bad
too atomized is probably bad we have to
find the soft spot in between
of small but but but
consequential local communities well
connected among themselves
yes i think the most important is that
there's people basically get off their
butt
and get together and start trying out
and i mean we'll figure out is the
right size 10 people 100 people 10 000
we don't know
but like in liberstad right now we have
access to clean water
or a cell phone our own property we have
enough forest
to heat ourselves and we can also make
our own food production
right if if we had to move somewhere
like you've had to move to
uh as you mentioned a hotel or or some
somewhere else
i wouldn't have the ability to even
create food right i would
i would have to use fiat currency i
would have to
pay taxes and whatever but if you have a
community that at least can do the
basics so you can do food production and
you can pay the first
person producing that food in an
anonymous
private transaction you're not paying
any taxes at all
and i think like but the most important
is just that
more and more people try this and do
this and see where we can get
i think that's super important
agreed time to to try out and
move i i personally agree
in the meanwhile we can see the proposal
uh by shinobi to
basically attach kyc data to every
transaction but
everyone uses someone else's kyc info
which is a very good proposal
i think that's excellent
it is symmetrical to uh another idea
that i was discussing with people i
don't know
if you uh if you think it's feasible
assuming that most
wallets are still basically vulnerable
to dust attacks
the idea would be to to coinjoin a lot
and then to use dust from coinjoin
attaching it to
all the biggest addresses of uh
of uh people in uh exchanges who
uh basically uh use a uh
coinjoin-based flags so if you
or even in general to be to be simpler
you take the
hugest uh addresses in bitcoin
and you just attack them with coinjoin
stuff
assuming that they're using a wallet
that will eventually
uh spend the the same kind of uh
they would they will randomly spend it's
possible that they will spend
together with the ugtxo also the dust
from the kyc
sorry from the conjoined stuff so we
could effectively
uh taint uh most of
huge bitcoin addresses but i don't know
if if this makes any sense
i mean i feel like chain analytics
companies would just very quickly
start disregarding obvious dustings like
that
and then also i i completely forget
who brought this idea up to me before
but a big risk i think there
would be distinguishing what addresses
you're actually hitting
like you know if you just like
hit some deposit address at an exchange
with
some tainted output and that winds up
being some user's
individual exchange address instead of
like some hot wallet
or cold storage for the exchange itself
then you're just [__] that user like
how can that user
like prove they didn't deposit that or
like they had nothing to do with that
and like i specifically no but i've
specifically
had um a buddy who had his coinbase
deposit address dusted like that
and coinbase support had no clue what
the [__] was going on
like he he was he literally was just
like this is not my money
i did not deposit that get that off my
account and they were like whoa we can't
uh i don't know what's going on but like
you're not the one who has to deal with
that problem
that user is yeah but if you ten
thousands
exactly like the company has to deal
with it and the user support
has to deal with it right and this means
that enforcing
the censorship based on chain analysis
becomes more and more
a costly uh essentially the reality is
what would happen is they would freeze
those things they would lock people out
of their money they wouldn't give two
shits about it
um people would start bitching about it
and then whatever company got affected
what do you mean they have to deal with
it no we're following the law
this is that user's problem hey they
might even spin that
pr wise to make people like us look like
[__]
and turn people against privacy tools
and against people like us because the
exchange can go it's all these [__]
fault
yeah but still i mean right now
exchanges are using
a heuristics that are technically
invalid so they are assuming for example
that
uh that that money was coming from your
friend
which was false so they are basing
actions on false premises and
i i'm not sure if stressing out in a
white hot way so be being careful not to
hurt too much somebody but uh stressing
out the fact that these heuristics
are basically just fake so that the fact
that for example
the heuristic that in every bitcoin
transaction uh
every kind of input comes from the same
party
is the fake heuristic if you if you [__]
that up
they you said before that they can
trivially
target obvious dust attacks but even in
in excluding obvious dust attacks from
from the analysis they are forced to
dispel the narrative of the simple
heuristic and they have to introduce
nuance basically they have to say
okay we cannot say anymore that every
time that you have
a connection with the conjoining your in
your transaction graph
then you maybe should be freezed we can
only say that
excluding obvious dust attacks and so
you can start to just
attack yourself a lot and then you can
say that it's not it was not you
conjoining i mean
we open up a lot of kind of ambiguities
and a lot
of kind of uh plausible known ability
paths of course
somebody may be heard of that but i mean
eventually if you are dealing with an
exchange which is going to censor
yourself
become because bitcoin is used for
privacy
you already [__] i mean i don't think
that the user that can be [__] by
coinbase
if they uh freeze conjure stuff
is going to be safe anyway even
disregarding any kind of action
eventually they are [__]
regardless well i mean like giacomo you
can instantly tell
a real coin join from a dust attack in
just analyzing amounts
and common sense heuristics like you
have a whole coin joined output versus
some taint in a dust output and
like two like i think you guys are not
thinking through
the public perception angle of this like
you
doing something like that will cause
problems for users it will
be their problem business won't give a
[__] they're just following the law
and that that is so easy to just spin
and blow up and privacy advocates face
and just get normal people
pissed at us instead of pissed at the
business
and like you know on top of that dude
they'll just say
i don't give a [__] like look at
companies like block fi
like bottle pay they don't give a [__]
we don't want
your coin joint stuff that's our
interpretation of the law
we're scared of it they won't care
yeah it's good they are bad actors and
it's good that users recognize that
every company
behaving lately these are bad actors
because it's just like a browser
telling you that you cannot use https if
a browser tells you that they will not
allow you to navigate https
pages this is a very shitty browser and
everybody was uh
was basically involved with internet
development or or browser development
it should be clear and obvious the
statement that
any kind of browser will behave like
that is a super shitty browser to be
which is compromised and is to be
avoided so
uh like if blockfi is preventing users
from using bitcoin
with security best practices uh i mean
it's an operator
block file is just a super bad actor
that has to be cut out as that
but like like giacomo that's our point
of view
that's our perspective as people
have been here for years for political
reasons
for political motivations not just
making money
that's not most people most people won't
care most people won't see that as a big
deal
or a bad thing because of their
perception based on legacy systems
and when you try to do something to
advocate for privacy in a way
that will just cause problems and
headaches and friction
for that type of person they're not
going to turn around
and go we should use privacy tools
they're going to go
[__] you you're the [__] responsible
for me not being able to touch my money
for three weeks
you know that brings my like i'm just
wondering now if some of these like
chain analysis companies or someone
is actually like listening why wouldn't
they do that
and just try to like shift the blame
towards
like coin joiners or like you know
they could easily do right now i don't
think they would
because the the key of their uh
marketing is that the chain analysis uh
heuristics are realistic which is a
which is often a fair statement
because right now many users are
i mean many many transactions are
probably
uh really made by the same entity on the
input sides
and many transactions really are not
paid join so i have just
one payment and one change and so this
is still realistic
it's not generally true anymore and
especially it cannot be used
in in a court as something scientific
because
it is not proven but it's a generally
pro
probable uh assumption in general
but the they can only make money if they
keep
up the narrative that they can track
bitcoin
if they do something like does attacks
making
creating entropy not just in the chain
but in the narrative
they are going to damage their their
sales speech
because their sales speech is bitcoin is
completely trade uh
traceable which is absolutely not true
uh but but it's it
it's their marketing stand
so sorry um i i think
what what would be good for them if
bitcoin would be
more and more private because
that means there are more and more
problems to solve for
them and charge money right so that
would be good
for them for their business
i think in that case there would be the
classical distinction between what is
good
to a business sector in general and to
incumbents
of a business sector so in general for
example what is good for
gun producers is gun freedom because you
can sell more guns
but what is good for beretta is gun
restrictions because then you basically
stop the competition
from entering your space so it is it's
not trivial the the incumbents usually
they want uh they don't want what
increases the the sector in general they
want
uh stuff that can prevent people from
competition and this
chain analyzes company uh they they have
huge databases of information
and destroying the reliability of the
heuristics that they use
to to sell these databases as a factual
connection
instead of just the probabilistic
assumptions
uh i'm i'm it would be good for new kind
of actors like
if generalized if trivial chain analysis
has been destroyed now it's time for
smart
detectives to come
out and sell their detective services
as opposed to the failed generalized
so the new entities can come out and
they can say
you know guys you cannot just follow the
blockchain
and infer uh everything like like they
used to do
because that's not realistic anymore you
actually have to hire
us in order to be smart and to and to
bug
people and to uh and to backdoor
software
and to physically uh use social
engineering to
uh uh call people and ask questions i
mean
you have to hire us to do detective work
and that is the good
sales speech for new entities which come
to replace
something like chain and isis but
generalizes right now are just saying
everything in bitcoin is traceable
publicly
and the only thing that you need is a
good database of
public addresses uh with some tags and
we have the hugest one
and so uh just pay us and we can tell
you something that you could
you can just see yourself but you won't
because there is division of labor so
pay us instead so i i think that
privacy would be good for detectives but
privacy would not be good for incumbent
chain analysis
companies based on the voodoo mystical
uh superstition that that that
that conjoints don't exist that lighting
doesn't exist
and that uh and that pageoid doesn't
exist and coinswap doesn't exist
and several steps uh before and after
uh are always different entities and all
this kind of arrested that are
completely fake
all right but i mean even even lightning
has a lot of privacy weaknesses
in its current implementation that
academia has been poking through
like there are numerous ways to
systematically
um probe the network time and analyze
things i mean any public channel
literally tells you publicly what their
channel utxos are
like there is so much work to be done
to actually make lightning something
that really breaks heuristics in a
systematic way
like we need schnoors so that we can do
ring signatures on tap root outputs
instead of doxing specific utxos
we need a lot more thought to like
timing latency and analysis
for payments we need um to replace pre
images
um and hash locks with adapter
signatures or
payment points like so many things
need to be upgraded on lightning to
actually systematically
shatter chain alice's heuristics like
that
and like lightning is nowhere close to
i'm not sure that you are right in the
specific
phrasing i mean uh let's just assume for
example that
i mean we are still not there so if you
think about
lighting as it is right now the network
you are absolutely right 100 but even
just
very very uh trivial evolutions of the
system like
people that are that in order to uh to
use lighting and save space
instead of creating two outputs one of
the payment and one
for the change they just open a channel
and they pay
they pay just part of the channel to the
payee so
they basically don't create uh the
change
this is this will not be strong privacy
because still you can probe
you can do it you can do time
correlation you can do a lot of stuff
and when you close the channel they will
see a lot of stuff
but this is assuming that this happens
this is breaking in a strong heuristic
which is
every uh every transaction has a few
inputs which are coming from the same
person and two
outputs one of which is the change this
is basically
one of the core assumption of of
every kind of uh complex uh
channels if you shatter this one of
course you open up
new ones but it's complex to re i mean
my point would be
it's true that you are still leaving a
lot of
surface surfaces of privacy
attack but you even if you just
shatter some few core assumption you are
increasing the complexity of our
analysis a lot
yeah it's true but there's one still
is that you can still find out what the
change output is so to say
in the closing transaction of the
lightning channel right as this gets
paid out to both alice and bob
and so your problem is not solved it's
just
pushed to one transaction later and also
like you still have individual node
operators
creating utxo clusters in channel
management
like the the bulk of payments still go
through a very small percent of nodes
that with that connectivity and
information could
de-anonymize a lot of [__] potentially
like
lightning is is nowhere close to
shattering those heuristics like that
and these types of companies and players
are already
like thinking through and finding new
heuristics
for lightning as it is right now
is that they uh in order to probe the
latin network
you have to at least provide liquidity
and at the same time while you spy
so the chain analysis are complete 100
leeches
they are spying without doing anything
while
lightning spies they at least have to
provide
routing capability and liquidity because
otherwise they are not really
uh surveying a lot so that's already a
nice
difference yeah but that's like
comparing like facebook facebook is
paying a lot for the servers
and we're paying and they're taking the
data
that's the value it would be the same
with a big lightning note
yeah in a way well i mean i i guess the
question is that
can lightning be potentially made
private sufficiently private
or it is or does it not even have the
potential
right it has potential yeah it
absolutely does but a bunch of the
primitives
that it's built on right now need to be
ripped out and totally replaced first
and by the way i just wanted to mention
if someone is interested that's why we
are here
exactly tldr that's lightning in wasabi
3.0
and yeah someone is interested about
these issues
on the current lightning network i
recommend to check out uh join the
wasabicars episode seven
where max was talking with isuan cerres
uh
about this like different kind of ways
to
acquire information about like private
channels and
taking snapshots off the network and
knowing by that
where things are moving i think there's
also some research into
building i don't i think it was building
an alternative lightning network or
building it
into the lightning network but
researched into adding
stuff from zcash into the lightning
network which would be easier to do than
adding it on the base layer of bitcoin
hey nopara did you actually just play a
master ball
to catch janine
hello
uh anyway this uh i can ask you guys to
uh link me uh this episode in the chat
if if you may just to to check out
because for example this is computer
related
but uh for my [__] shitcoin
rgb stuff we basically ended up not
reusing
um the ldk
raster implementation as we were imaging
so a few guys maxim and others they are
recreating as a lighting node from
scratch
which is super annoying but uh there was
no simple alternative the
adapting ldk was more annoying so
uh maybe there are thank you maybe there
is uh there is some opportunity to
uh to try to help out these uh this uh
privacy oriented lighting stuff etc
uh it could be interesting
i mean it's mostly just like we need
schnorr and taproot so that you can have
a
ddos protection for channels to route
payments
so that you don't just waste time with
non-existent [__] and then we need
um adapter signatures to replace hash
locks
like those
sorry and what we saw before opening
uh lightning channels yes please
yes and also i i mean even if you would
use bobby zombie to break the peeling
chain of one note opening multiple
channels
you still need to somehow obfuscate that
one class or one node controls all of
these channels
which is a bit more tricky to do in the
lightning model
yeah then there are i guess there are
also if you
improvements you can do in a path
discovery algorithm
right now they're they usually are very
simple and based on
efficiency because still it's not
trivial to pay
especially large amounts like
a few hundred bucks it's difficult to
find liquidity so
uh so paths are very very trivial
while probably you can try to make them
a little bit more
uh complex uh introducing uh
time delays and and compulsory steps
uh in order to avoid the the most
efficient
and to introduce a degree of uh
sacrifice of efficiency and liquidity in
order to preserve a
better privacy
yeah i mean also i guess
sorry
no it's just uh also in general i think
that
for example the way you you do lighting
right now
is super still so early for example
uh you have the typical situation the
typical workflow
where uh i i give you for example i open
btc
page server page and i will have a
lighting invoice if the guy
check it for lighting first and then if
i if i
am paying too much then i have to move
on the
second tab on the page to go to get
a light a non-chain address
while it would be probably i think it
will happen that eventually
your default invoicing strategy will be
just to share
some kind of like onion or something
where you connect with the receiving
server and the server will just propose
you
like what are you going to do if your
guard if you need something
huge maybe open a channel with me but
not manually just
automatically and if you don't just uh
just route through me
or or pay join to me or whatever i mean
i think there are a lot of stuff
that can incentivize the um the
the development of the network even just
from the ux point of view because right
now
right now if i can pay you on like like
i
i've won a a bet with uh with eric wool
and he had to pay me uh 1 000 bucks
on lightning no actually he had to pay
me 1 000 bucks
but then in order to troll me because he
was a third loser he
he asked he told me invoice me and i
will pay online
and i did and he did pay but it was of
course
super complex because it was uh yet to
find the liquidity first to consolidate
and stuff
but most of this stuff will probably uh
become more and more automatized which
will probably have
a few kind of consequences on privacy as
well
i mean not necessarily like lightning
pool
is a big potential there um
because you can disconnect who's
actually paying for your receiving
liquidity from who's providing it
um that's a lot of potential but really
i think the the two
biggest things from like systemic
privacy improvements in lightning are
one like you said introducing um
like extra latency along a payment path
but then also assuming you have
um adapter signatures instead of hash
locks
so that each hop is decorated um
multi um path routing too so breaking
the payment up like that
so i like i i think of it as kind of two
separate ways you can attack the problem
um the latency introduction prevents the
the kind of systematic timing analysis
but it introduces some ux friction but
on the other side if you have
no pre-image or hash lock to correlate
then if you just break the payment up
and if there's
enough people and enough money flowing
that's doing
the uh multi-pronged routing like that
then like that also does the same thing
without the the big ux
friction because like how are you going
to correlate all the
the parts of a payment into a single
amount when
everybody's breaking their payments up
like that
yep yep i also think that right now the
default for
a lightning user is basically to fire up
a node with with a public
uh mostly with the broadcasting the
public name
and something like that while eventually
we cannot go to the same extent to the
the on-chain experience where we
create a new address for every
transaction because that will not make
any sense
but probably we will have some kind of
compromise where the typical
uh lighting node can fire up at least
uh i don't know 10 or or 20
uh small nodes that will create channels
independently and then
route through them in order to to serve
the same kind of user
seamlessly i mean it's a little bit
paradoxical that
when you when you onboard somebody
lighting it just fires up
one node and exposed the in the worst
case scenario even the home ip address
attaching it to that node
yeah giacomo did you make some thinking
about how to initiate
those um uh like user-to-user
communications for
in-ways handshakes and such
yeah there was uh still in our
meta scam rgb project there has been
uh some discussion for a this kind of
universal invoicing
stuff that we checked up with a few
lighting developers uh like chris and
decker and
i i'm not sure about well i think maxim
talked with somebody
and there was some discussion the point
is
that uh everything that we are doing
which is
close to rgb stuff tends to be seen as
uh
mostly very connected with this asset
idea and not with the rest well this is
a very general
thing so i'm i was trying to involve
more
more people maybe talk with you know
allen
uh for uh for standards and i mean more
more standard oriented people
in order to understand if there is
ground to to think about a beep
in theory it's pretty simple because you
have
uh you have two cases one case
is the one in which you will be online
at the time
of the payment so in this case you just
need a reachable address which can be
uh uh which it can just be an onion that
you can also set up just for
the single communication so it doesn't
even need to be universal
and then you can you can just have back
and forth
of course with uh with the counterparty
that knows how to read that
and you can have a full back which can
be just a simple address if the
counterparty doesn't understand
and the second case which is way more
complex is when you assume that you may
not be online
at the time of the payment and then you
have to basically
tell i have to tell your wallet if i'm
not online at this address
then you shall should try either this
kind of uh
third-party proxy or this zone chain
address so in that case it becomes
way more complex but in theory the the
case in which you are online which on
lightning is basically the default case
anyway
should be simple i mean speak to me here
and then uh we will do everything uh
interactively in in theory which could
also include
uh the main point would be pay me but if
you can't
open a channel and maybe let's pay join
in order to open this channel
it would be cool
i mean all of that's definitely
optimizations
that are necessary and i'm 100
with you that like interaction between
users
like it's going to be interactive like
you can't
just have static information as the
whole protocol stack builds up you're
going to need to interact
but it's i i really think
like the biggest privacy gain from
lightning would be
like breaking the timing analysis for
payments and side lightning and then
we need ring signatures on um
snore outputs instead of like
actually doxing your unique utxo
like we need some way of proving you
have money to route stuff with without
showing the exact utxos hey actually a
question here should know be
does do these proof have to be within
one transaction so that it's only the
outputs of a single transaction that are
covered
in that ring or is it multi-transaction
outputs
well no it would be like a ring
signature with all
or a bunch of other tap root outputs so
like you prove
i control a taproot output of bitcoin
like i proved i actually have bitcoin
but i'm not telling you
which specific utxo like public channels
do now to prove they can actually route
your money
but don't you need to know the
transaction out point
just to build the ptlc
no um they like you just pass the
information
along in the onion um wraps needed
for those channel parties to construct
that
like you you don't need to know all the
the details of that you just need to
give them what they need to make the
right transaction output
wait so what information do you pass on
to route members
well the hash lock if it's a hash lock
or
if it's a um a uh
adapter signature you get the point from
the receiver
and then you construct the uh numbers
and then just wrap those in the uh
the different onion hops so that they
can make the right adapter signature
yeah so only the channel body needs to
know the exact output
like the only reason that's doxxed in
the routing tables now
is so that you know where you're trying
to route a payment to
actually has a channel and isn't some
guy with nothing just laughing like huh
he's going to route a payment and it's
going to fail because i don't even have
a channel open
and told you prevent that case
well i mean that that would be the point
of replacing that with
um like a ring signature on schnoor
outputs
because instead of having to publicly
dox
like your actual utxon chain you just
prove
that you have one of this whole pool and
so it still gives the same ddos
resistance of like i'm actually
i hold bitcoin i can do bitcoin and
stuff
and do these outputs of the ring have to
be the same denomination
um i'm not exactly 100
sure on the restrictions and limitations
um
jonas nick wrote a quick uh
just that he threw up on github i want
to say like
five or six months ago
for the ring signatures themselves it
makes absolutely no difference
uh all of ring signature is a is a
logical or
of several keys uh what does matter is
like you're verifying that the ring the
set of keys
actually corresponds to some utxos that
are unspent on chain and
then it's just a matter of like what
lower bound will you accept
like if you need somebody to prove that
they have this much locked up
then any output larger than that that
they know the key of is
sufficient
but it's like you know with without
obscuring
the specific utxo information
chain analysis has the entire graph of
public channels and what utxos those
correspond to to work with
yeah you still have a little bit of
confusion
brought by uh the private channels but
are very few and not not easy to
to use to route through so yeah and you
actually can kind of deduce a lot about
private channels as well
because of the long-term channel
management clustering
on chain um as like a nodes managing and
opening and closing channels yep that's
where non-announced channel fails
is in privacy if we would use coin joins
in between each of these private channel
openings that would be much better
plus taproot to avoid the script type
so a question for for the ones of you
who may be more uh
more close to the development of
something lightly related
uh do you think that with taproot uh
the basic of the the implementation that
we use right now of lighting will have
to be
written fundamentally anyway so instead
of just being an enabler
of this kind of stuff taproot may also
be
i would say an enforcer of of restarting
with lighting a little bit because we
have to change a lot in order to have
uh topper closings it's not like you
have an easy
i mean you cannot easily easily use
current implementation to open and close
the uproot version of life in china's i
guess
yep we're about to find out exactly how
much
is baked into implementation instead of
generalized to plug-and-play
as far as lightning implementations
because
anyways i think we'll have to wait for
l2
as another well
change in the building blocks i was
saying the same exactly it's a little
bit sad that cigars no input or
equivalents are not in in this round
because
probably it will require another
basically
refactoring of the entire channel
structure
dude i am so pissed that
any prevout is not in taproot like with
all the time
being wasted on stupid bike shutting
argument it's like
so why didn't we just put that in here
too i mean if we're if we're going to
sit here and argue for the next year
why not
yeah we should do a uasf for uh for
anybody
operation full [__] could do a second
release
[Laughter]
how's it going there are you forked off
yet
last time i checked nope by the way
is there some nice automated way to
check the
current block height uh and hash from
different nodes and get an alert when
they differ
um electrum has that built in
like it'll tell you if any of the
servers it's connected to diverge
with a warning
yeah but something that i can put on top
of my own nodes
just spin up an electrum server man and
then put electrum on it
and yeah and connect one electron client
to both servers
and only those two servers yeah no
you wouldn't need to uh connect to the
server
because it still does the spv proof
for multiple stuff in addition to the
balance querying from
the back end
what do you guys think um yeah uh
are you interested in talking about like
a little bit of austrian economics
um yeah we can continue about this
i would love that yeah i had a
sure question for giacomo about it but
yeah it might need a little bit like for
others to
know what we're talking about uh like in
austrian economics you have this like
homesteading principle and that's pretty
much like
how you acquire uh yourself something
like you mix your work with the land for
example i'm not sure if i'm
phrasing this correctly but that's
pretty much about
it and there has been like many
different views of like
austrian economics on how does that
practically
would work and i used to like the
like the most that i liked uh was the
wrote guardians a rothbard's version of
it which
was well it has some downsides but i
think giacomo
and i think it was uh stefan kinsella
who
at least to my knowledge came up with
this or
introduced me to this um kind of like
i think it was like a physical causality
which would kind of like determine uh
what would you actually own and
it's a little bit like a i think it
interesting concept
uh maybe max or giacomo you can uh
rephrase a little bit of
or explain this a little bit better
i would just like to uh to try to
separate a little bit
austrian economics from uh let's say
liberty
libertarian ethics and uh narco
capitalist ethics which are
very very close usually because i think
you may say
uh in a fair way that uh that
uh i mean uh austrian economics is uh
a a direction a family of uh
of uh australian think of thinkers
we started in austria with uh with
menger
and uh boom bakker and
uh and then mises and nayak and even if
and then rothbar
and then lately maybe hope and kinsell
himself
and you may say that this is the natural
economic framework
for a libertarian ethic theory
uh and then you may say that there is a
libertarian ethnic theory
which is dating back to to ancient times
but it was explicitly
uh it was made explicit first by
probably in the most complete way by
john locke which was also
one of the first guys ex make making the
homesteading principle explicit
it was john locke was not at all an
austrian economist in any in any regard
but you may say that austrian economics
is the natural
economic uh argument
for the good economic consequences of
property rights as defined in
libertarian theories
then you have a few guys especially
later on like after
mises which you can probably call
an uncap in some ways because well this
is a little bit complex but
mises was basically miser believed that
mises believed that you need a state
but the state must in order to be
legitimate it must concede uh
individual secession so if you want to
secede from the state with your own
property
you can otherwise the state is not
legitimate anymore
which is basically it's another way to
get to the same conclusions
of rothbard about nations by consent
and private security companies and stuff
like staff stuff like that
so you can say that mises and rothbard
and
and hope and this and kinsella
are libertarians and um
and also economists while many western
economies are not libertarian like hayek
himself
is not and menger was certainly not and
especially the the the first
economic economists were basically not
and the other way around you can find
many libertarians and
caps which are maybe not convinced by
some of the core uh assumption
of the austrian uh insight into economic
theory
uh from the so just a very quick
uh i try to summarize a little bit uh
the insights of economic austin austin
school of economics
is basically about uh the first one is
about uh
marginal marginal uh utility
and uh it's about marginality
marginalism
so the fact that uh demand and uh
supply interact uh in in
in a way which is based on
it so let's try to to frame it in a
simplified way like this
instead of the labor theory of value
by by people like adam smith
you have the explicit theory that
the price the value is coming from
interaction of
demand and supply curves with this this
insight about
uh about the marginal utility
going down when you increase your your
consume
you're consuming and and the second
inside was time like the the time
component of
inflation and money and the business
cycle the fact that
if you print money and distribute it
this is not neutral because you will
have
this kind of cantilove phenomenons you
will have a restructuring in the
in the production structure uh that will
follow the
the flow of money so there is a lot of
beautiful stuff from
from menger already about the business
cycle and then
from from mayak and and that from others
so the importance of time i would say
and the importance of
demand and supply marginal uh
characteristic
these are the base insides while
libertarianism is basically
based on the fact that you can have a
consistent ethics
which is based on homesteading and
contracts so which just two ethical
primitives
which is homesteading of unappropriated
natural resources
and uh and uh and respect of
uh mutual agreements you can have
a a more just and or
a more effective society based on the
fact that you are more like
um a consecutive consequentialist
uh which is the latter case you just
care that the society
is better like more efficient
or you are like a like uh
ethical uh
what is name um well i remember the
proper name but basically
you uh you want to do something which is
ideological
not just consequentialist you are
deontologically libertarian
and uh so i'm studying principle there
are a lot of discussion
uh recent discussion by kinsella and
others
that can differ in the definition of um
stadium for example john locke himself
he made a pretty uh a pretty simple
statement which is
whenever you come across something which
is unappropriated
and you mix your labor with it then you
own it
and there have been some simple
traditions
uh that have a very uh naive
interpretation of this like if i if i
come to a land
which is desert and then i plant some
seeds
now i own the land but usually stuff are
more complex because for example in
comollo in
in customary laws everywhere they
already wear
many bundles of sticks representing
different kind of rides for example
if i walk into a wood then i'm
appropriating the wood
with some specific use which is working
but that doesn't prevent me
as long as i can work again from if i
create a path
on the wood that doesn't prevent
that doesn't allow me to prevent
somebody else
from planting seeds and and harvesting
fruits
in the same wood or to use the wood as
uh as a as basically uh
source of of fuel for
fire or something else so the kind of
it's not like you appropriate a pla a
piece of land
like in the homesteading acts of the
united states and
and then you own everything which is
below and everything which is above
including
stars and satellites you just own the
the the causal effects
of the action that you perform on
appropriating parts of reality so if you
do something
everything which is crucially coming out
of that some
action is basically your right to
enjoy the effects in a a
undisturbed and if somebody disturbs you
then you you can react and this is this
is another important part of
of libertarian ethics which is how can
you react
which is the all the discussion about
the proportional reaction like if if if
i come to your
land and without any kind of a gra
of of a threat of a
threat and any kind of very aggressive
behavior
i just put one feet inside
the the border of your land can you just
shoot me in
in the head because of that or not and
there are a
lot of discussions and different
interpretation of proportionality of
reaction
and in especially about these uh stephen
kisela stephen kisela is
is very very uh i think is very very
interesting because he's using
uh like hope they are mostly using
logics
in order to justify this stuff and in
particular about
proportional reaction they are using a
stop argument like
if you deny one right to me
then you are performatively
contradicting yourself when you climb
claim the same right to yourself which
is true
under the assumption of universalism of
course which is not
an obvious assumption so it's a very
complex argument but
i would say my main response would be
we are discussing two different things
there is an ethical theory
and there is an economic framework uh
the economic framework
uh is natural for the economical for the
ethical theory and vice versa
but they are not the same thing and you
can have an austrian economist which is
not
and a rothbard libertarian and you can
bet
you can have an anarcho-capitalist which
is not uh
austrian at all like many classical
liberals like
like even bastiata i mean it doesn't
make sense to say that
bastiat was austrian
uh but it was clearly ironcap
libertarian
and uh so you have a lot of different
flavors
but uh i think that
the the austrian economics was basically
successful at the end it was uh until
the until the late uh uh
until the second part of the 20th
century
uh there was uh well until the 70s
there was basically most great part of
the
as far as i know i'm not an economist
myself but great part of the
mainstream academic consensus was
incorporating
most of the cases of manga and vogue
and high and even hayek and and even
mises
in a way and while liberty
ethical libertarianism was mostly always
rejected and
they had the the ethical part of the
of the modern academic consensus never
really
uh made the rothbard mainstream
uh especially outside the united states
but ocean economics was becoming
more and more my stream it changed back
kind of recently a few decades ago when
there was a
a a recruiter sensor there was basically
a
uh it was a basically
a renaissance of canis and [__]
all all the way
around everywhere basically so
yeah very very long answer but it was
just to separate the two topics that you
mentioned
yeah i think that's a really good thing
that you did uh
yeah good points and i just wanted to
emphasize a little bit more like uh as
far as i understood
previously there was a lot of these like
talks that uh
this like homesteading principle would
kind of like give you the permission
for example if you get a piece of land
for yourself you would own
everything below it in like a cone shape
and everything
above it uh like yeah
airplanes or whatever goes above your
house or something like that
but i guess i think it was like a
rothbard who actually argued that you
don't
own any of the air or the ground below
you
because you are not using it and i think
that was already like a really good
um like way to move forward much more
like logical thing
that if for example under your uh under
your house there's a lot of oil
if someone else can actually go on and
get it without
like making any damage to your house or
to your
land that's totally okay to do
but yeah i think yeah this idea of this
physical causality is even
makes much more sense than what any of
the
the views that i've saw or heard uh
previously
so just as an example like uh yeah
whenever you plant a tree
you don't own the as if i understood
correctly
this physical causality wouldn't mean
that you own the land
uh per se but actually the the tree that
you have
planted and all the fruits that it
produces or whatever
and of course the immediate land that is
next to your tree because it
actually needs it but yeah i think
that makes sense but i'm i'm wondering a
little bit like how far can it
can we take it uh how like let's say
if you plant this tree it's pop it does
have roots
but it's not just those roots that you
or the tree will use but it will connect
to let's say some kind of like
mycelium network and trade a lot of like
resources throughout
like let's say forest so could someone
go on and you know do something for that
forest
if it kind of like hurts your tree i'm
i'm just interested about like
what is your reasoning or thoughts
behind this
where's the line yeah first of all i
think it's
it will be i mean it's fair to recognize
to acknowledge that rothbar was
the first modern libertarian thinker to
clarify this a little bit together with
other people like
block and others but uh actually
i i think that the the the good way to
to
to explain this is that it was already
like that
in most customary rights uh
setups so like in england customer
rights and stuff
before the 17th century most
customary laws coming from middle ages
were already assuming this kind of
bundles of stick
in which there was something that was
not always called the homesteading but
was basically equivalent to the
setting principle was usually called the
um
the prior priority i think
precedence maybe it will be in english
president's rights
which is basically it's not even very
exotic it's the same kind of logic you
would use
instinctively even children would use
distinctively
when they come and on the spot and they
say
uh i i was it here is here first for
example
let's assume this you are going to the
beach and
you set up um and use
you put down your robe and your or your
chair
and you start to relax and sleep and
then
a few a few punks come along
with a very uh with a very
noisy music and they scream and dance
next to you
and they are basically disturbing you
and so you are pissed and you demand
uh the respect of your of the sport that
you elected
while on the other way around if you
imagine the symmetrical situation in
time in which
uh you arrive on a beach which is
which is empty and you start to dance
with your friends
and then one after three hours one
guy one nerd uh one [__] nerd comes
along
and he says oh guys stop i just want to
sleep here
i just want to put my chair here and i
want absolute silence
of course you would you would basically
start to insult him
uh because the point is is homesteading
right is
is precedence is time precedence when
you when you do something
first in order to uh to to change your
reality around you
which can also just be working in a
place is already changing reality around
you
because you are basically creating a
path in access you are
you're already extracting stuff from
from nature so
this was natural and indeed in uh
one of the tragedy of of the modern
times that
libertarians started to fight uh against
and and there was the
the tradition of the levelers in in
england where which were
connected with the uh the the
enlightenment of jolok and other people
it was about enclosures so the idea was
that
before some time societies
spontaneously developed more or less
analogous rules in which when you plant
something
you can get the stuff coming from that
plant
and when you pass in some field you
and your hairs will inherit the rights
of passage
and when you fence something you will
you will inherit the right to for to
defense
not to be uh broken unless
it was uh it was interfering
with an acquired uh passage right
so uh and if you uh there was there were
rights about uh
using wastelands in order to uh to
uh or grazing of cows or or hunting
hunting rights and whatever and very
complex
burdens of uh very complex bundles of
sticks
that had nothing to do with the naive
vision of the corn
starting from the center of the earth
and going into the start
then uh the uk government that was
actually one of the first
super nation states because after the
the harry day eight reformation uh the
the english crown
uh confiscated uh all the
catholic uh monasteries and stuff like
that so they became
uh overnight the the the
the the hugest uh owner
uh or or or at least uh
the hugest climate to to land property
in the hindu known ward and and they
started to do
enclosures they started to do uh to to
to close they started to do basically
fiat
uh fiat fiat geography
instead of emergent equilibrium of
different rights recognizing by customs
uh a single bureaucrat of the of the
english crown
will just assess and assign territories
with this notion of the center of the
earth until the stars
cone whatever is underground which
especially
destroyed any kind of more soft
more nuanced rights like passage rights
for for the cattle and the wasteland use
and so entire families were basically
disrupted
by this situation because they they
could not after generation and
generations they could not
anymore uh get wood on this place
or or gaze their cattle on this other
place
or just pass through this the path that
their
ancestors passed through for generations
because there was this kind of political
centralized redefinition of property
right
by by by state bureaucrats for the first
time in england
and and this basically went on in the
homesteading act of the united states
where
they were basically the frontier man the
the the
columns the uh claiming lands in the
united states
and the federal government was basically
using this kind of
english super naive version
and then rothbard got
back to a more traditional more natural
in a way
more spontaneous definition of property
rights that
he didn't invent that definition it just
got back to that definition which is
which was already typical our customary
rights
basically everywhere and of course what
i would say is that
not only is scales pretty well way
better than the
the cone theory uh for example because
otherwise you cannot
have oil extraction or or planes or
satellites
or even like space colonization you
cannot have that because
at some point uh mars will be
uh up uh just just uh stride up your
home
and then you you will have to you can
you will be able to claim
the the dimension of elon musk on mars
which would be problematic but even if
you think about
the discovery of electromagnetic waves
and
electromagnetic communication well that
pretty much
destroys the cone vision you your
property gets
uh crossed by electromagnetic wave all
the time
uh for any kind of purposes and and and
you cannot stop it
because it doesn't make any sense to
stop it otherwise you should be
you you will have to be able to prevent
everybody to
build an antenna everywhere for any kind
of purpose so you cannot say
i own this land and everything passing
by it
but you can say that any any kind of
phenomenon which
doesn't interfere with your enjoyment of
the kind of physical effects that you
produce with your actions
uh then that's legit and if it
interferes
then you can allegedly claim a
refund which is proportional to
interference of course now
there's the point of the of the
determination of
proportionality which is not trivial but
but it's but it's very straightforward
in this way
uh like as ma even smell uh smell is
basically
uh i mean i creating something in
reality
which will affect you and you are here
first and i'm coming here later so i
cannot
build something smelly next to your home
because you were here first but you can
create something smelly and i cannot
come here to pretend
to create something which is which is
safe from smell
next to you because you were here first
so uh
it it goes for electromagnetic waves
and um and uh and and noises
and views like uh uh
like um the view from your balcony on
the sea
uh or shadow from the sun and
more or less the fiat laws try to
emulate
this kind of agreements but of course
centralized fiat laws cannot
function because it's it's just a few
politicians and brokers trying to
recreate a spontaneous organization
which
which is basically central planning
which always fails
so it doesn't work but they try
to recreate something that was already
discovered by civilization
for for centuries which is this kind of
uh
precedence homesteading principle uh
which works basically with with
everything without
strong problems uh if if you think about
it another kind of modern
except for electromagnetic waves and tvs
and radios
another great point that would destroy
the naive consideration would be like
even just the
the the popular the popularized version
of
uh chaos theory uh everything you do
including like uh your butterfly
flying will cause major effects
in in uh
[Music]
in turbulence in uh in climate elsewhere
and so you may have an hurricane coming
from a butterfly
so the point is that uh
you you don't have any kind of insulate
you cannot have
your property insulated from any any
anything else
the only thing that you can have is the
right
uh front to to uh it's the right
basically to
uh claim complains proportional
compensation
if uh or or or uh and enforce
proportional retaliation which is
basically the same thing
uh because then the the offending party
can trade
retaliation with compensation uh
if you uh if the the
if you basically suffered interference
between
the natural consequences of your actions
and the action of other people so it's
pretty straightforward i think it works
pretty well
of course there are there are nuances
for example i i
dream to the debate with kinsella and we
set up in twitter
a debate in the future but we don't know
when we will make it
about the fact that he thinks that you
cannot have um
homesteading principle in a computer
network because
uh i mean if i if i stole your keys
somehow
that's not really theft from a
libertarian point of view
this doesn't really matter because
bitcoin is built in a way that
uh it doesn't matter who is right it
just
matter that it works in a way that that
maximize
uh self-sovereignty so it is not really
important
but i think it's it's it is interesting
to uh
stephen crystal has this strong
distinction between between
physical matter and information
and he says that you can have rights
property rights and physical
stuff but not in information and
i'm skeptical about this distinction
because
as a as a amateur physicist
i don't think there is any fundamental
distinction
between information and and physical
stuff like
like in a in a in a wheeler uh set up
uh it from bit uh i don't know if you
know what i'm talking about but i think
that information is more fundamental
of physical stuff so there may be the
same kind of generalized ethical theory
that applies to both but it doesn't
really make any practical difference
like
i agree with stefan's conclusion about
uh property right of
intellectual property and patents i 100
agree with him
i agree that bitcoin doesn't care
about ethical theories it just works so
it doesn't
it doesn't need uh analytical theory on
top
in order to work uh your key your
bitcoin and nobody can do anything about
that
so practically speaking i agree 100 with
him theoretically speaking i think that
i disagree in a few points and i also
think that contracts
that promises may be binding and he
disagrees about that
because of this fundamental distinction
between physical stuff
and and uh and information
hmm really interesting and yeah i will
be eagerly waiting for that debate
and yeah does anyone have any questions
it's not a actually actually a question
but it's more like
it's very interesting to listen to to
this stuff and it's also
sort of the foundation of of liberstad
and
all of these questions are very hard and
we're thinking about it a lot and
discussing ourselves a lot
in terms of like uh the rules of private
property i think that's something
a society has to figure out eventually
by himself because
you can't rationalize on what do you
really own and how much work do you have
to apply
to actually take ownership in something
and
the way we've at least initially now
handled this in liberstad is that
basically we're splitting up
the plots to people and that will be
your private plot where you can have
your cabin while the city center will be
at least initially fully owned by the
city company
but we actually want to divide the
ownership
and decentralize the whole thing so
and and not have our own ownership in it
because that
would make it harder for the government
or someone else to come in and take the
land because they will get
claims from let's say five
fifty thousand people who say that oh i
own this land you can't take it or do
what you
want with it but it's like uh
an important thing is to have a singular
entity that actually can control
and and decide what to do on a property
i think that's super important
instead of having like a democracy of
any kind because that
it's highly efficient inefficient and
you will
get into trouble right away so like uh
one final thing i want to mention is
like if you're a socialist or a
politician you're actually not
physically allowed to enter liberstad
and it's a membership organization
so you won't be able to become a member
unless you actually
support at least partially the
philosophy behind it
so you basically get people who doesn't
have to be a libertarian but at least
you're leaning toward
those ideas and sharing the concept
around those ideas
i think that's super important to be
able to build a community
around anarcho-capitalism and whatever
and
we can't there's no free land any longer
so we basically have to just
buy land and then claim that this land
is ours we paid for it here's your
contract
and if you're big enough you can just
say that
we control islam you have no authority
here
well i think it's important to
distinguish two couple of concept the
first
is the distinction between what is
alleged from a property rights point of
view
and what is smart from a strategic point
of view so of course
all kind of setup among consenting
parties which are appropriating
uh unappropriated resources
are legit from a property rights point
of view
including one guy owning everything and
then
renting out uh like the the the
libertarian dictator of the mental
experiment
or a democracy meaning like
like is a a shareholder
meeting of people voting with different
weights
so a weighted democracy of owners it's
it's something that can be used and can
work like
they use it in monasteries they using
some
pirate communes they use it in some i
mean it can work
uh maybe at some scale and complete the
centralization
of independent uh lumberjacks
and and trappers uh just staying on
their
specific range can work as well so you
can have different
legit configurations uh and of course
the nation state coming and taking your
money with force is not legit
but everything else is basically legit
but then only a few of this
configuration are also strategically
smart
and maybe you can say as you as you just
said
uh in theory we can have everybody can
have
their own land but in practice it's
better if we just
set up a central owner because because
you you always have the same
trade-off right decentralization is
anti-fragile
but inefficient and centralization
is fragile but efficient
and short-term you want efficiency
because without efficiency you cannot
really start anything
so short term you need some kind of
centralization to boost up stuff
even bitcoin will not exist without
satoshi nakamoto
if you wait for a spontaneous order
to make up a bitcoin without some guy
taking responsibility to start
something centralized nothing will will
come out of
spontaneous interaction without the
individual agency uh so you need the
satoshi to start a bitcoin
uh and then eventually you can you can
get rid of it
or he can get rid of himself uh but uh
the complete decentralization is an
efficient uh
as you said when you need to face a
common a common adversary like
like the government coming in you
probably need strong coordination
but if it's if it is too strong then you
have a single point of failure and you
will resist
better but when you fail everything will
fail with you
while if you have everyone for himself
you will not resist at all but you will
be
but but you will not but some but you
will mostly not resist
but the single pieces resisting will
resist for a very long time
so you have this trade-off between uh
efficiency and
and and anti-fragility and to
antifragility i would say yeah
uh and and the second distinction is
basically
between uh between i mean
what actually is your uh hidden goal
and your over overt and covert goal
basically
again as i said before if you go for the
overt libertarian and capitalist society
i it's legit it's also noble uh
but it may be strategically silly
because then you're basically giving
too much information to your
counterparty i think it's
on the other side if you go completely
covered
uh and you just pretend you are guys
doing stuff
maybe you will not make very clear the
purposes so you will
basically let in a lot of people with
conflicting ideas and then
you will have problems so you these
these are not
these are two trade-offs you you have to
stay in between uh too much centralized
is a problem
too much decentralized nothing worse uh
too much overt you are a target
immediately
and they will just stop you uh
immediately as
as long as soon as you become relevant
and overt
uh they will stop in an arc capitalist
society from working because
it is unacceptable and if you're too
covered
you can become compromised over time
because you're compromising your ideas
so it's it's very uh dedicated
very good points and i think just you
know i've been wondering
if we would have been able to like try
out
all of these different things freely uh
throughout the history
like in my opinion the better we have
different kind of options
the more different results we get and
the more we data and hence we can make
better decisions
but it would be interesting to yeah
like just to even talk think about it
like um
if we would have had the possibility to
create all these kind of different
societies
with different kind of rules with
different different kind of like
homesteading
uh if we would have come into already
better conclusions or if we already
would have much
better data of what to do
don't think that that kind of thing will
ever be practical
like in my mind the entire
issue of rights is utterly arbitrary
but completely based on
how long are you liable for the
consequences of something
like you do something that ripples
forever with further consequences
that adds causal links to your initial
action
causing other things and the entire
debate is entirely around how many
causal hops
how long and that that entire
fundamental dynamic in human history
it shifts when people are capable when
they're
self-sufficient they want them as short
as possible
as few hops as little time but the more
[__] up [__] gets
the the more incapable of sustaining
themselves or being self-sufficient
the longer people want that time window
to be
where people are responsible for
something the more
causal hops and right now
the world is turning into a really
[__] up
place so how do you think most people in
the world
are going to approach that debate of
what are rights where do they start and
stop
so i very much agree with kinsella and
hope
that rights if they have a meaning
if they have an objective meaning so an
inter-subjective meaning
at all are basically grounded in logics
which is not very i mean your discussion
of causal
links are is basically in my opinion the
very foundation
of everything which is related with the
property rights and
i'm studying principle and and so on
it's just an application of
logics uh if so either
there is something right and something
wrong
or not if you take the moral
morally relativistic position that there
is nothing right or wrong
then uh that's that's a legit position
but then every kind of discussion is
already over
it's just a matter of uh power uh
if uh if i i'm not surprised i'm not
saying that at all
no no i know but if somebody takes the
morally relativistic
point then the discussion is it's legit
but it's over
uh if i see a girl and i want the girl
uh it's it's it's not in just to rape
her
as long as they have the capability of
doing that and get away with that
if i can do it and get away then it's
just for me to do it
by definition if instead you came to the
position that there is an objective
right and wrong and somebody powerful
can do something wrong
but still be wrong then you can start to
argue and then there is a
all this this field of argumentative
argumentation and ethics
that basically say that when you argue
that there is something right
you cannot assume anything which is
performatively contradictory
to the fact that you are arguing which
is basically for example
if you assume that there is no property
right into your body
you cannot even discuss stuff because
you cannot use your body in a way that
doesn't suit your
your uh that your counterpart in this
discussion
so there are all this set kind of
argumentation
the argument that goes from pure logic
into some objective definition of
property rights and i think that's
a legit operation to do and grounds
property rights
into the laws of logic themselves of
course this doesn't mean
that there is a simple way to assign
property rights
which is infallible and obvious because
i mean we know basic laws of physics at
least to a certain approximation but
that doesn't mean that we can easily
reconstruct
starting from the schrodinger equation
uh uh
the the movement of molecule in my my
glass of water
we can't because just too much stuff
going on there we know
a good approximation of the basic laws
and we know they are coming
and we know that chemistry uh comes from
uh from quantum field theory basically
from quantum mediterranean dynamics we
know that
uh with good approximation but we and we
uh that hydrodynamics inside my glass of
water comes from chemistry
but i cannot really use this principle
to
to to settle every kind of question uh i
still
there is still margin for a mistake and
it's kind of my
point you're ignoring
the entire variable of time horizon
like you say if you walk up to somebody
and shoot them in the face
you did something wrong you're gonna get
punished for that
that was wrong and i would agree with
that
but somebody else who's going to plug in
a different variable in that time
horizon or a different
variable in how many causal hops
you have to be responsible for and
they're gonna go you driving your car
around the city all day is creating
smog and even though you the single
driver doing that
isn't the reason that i have [__]
lung cancer you're partially responsible
and it's entirely about that variable of
time
horizon that people define
rights and view them and you will never
get consensus on that globally
you will you will never in my opinion
see this
proliferation of smaller independent
areas
except on the edges of bigger ones
because the world is getting
[__] up and it's getting harder and
harder to take care of yourself
so more and more people are going to
fill in longer time
horizons in that equation of what is a
right
i think there are two points that you're
making one is that the majority of
people especially now will not accept
this kind of
ethical framework and i agree with that
it's independent from the fact that the
ethical framework is right or wrong is
is logical or is logically consistent or
not it's just that
it's not very fashionable right now to
talk about property rights
no what i'm saying is they're going to
plug a different variable
into that framework than you or i would
so yeah this was what i will have said
as the second
point back in your in your objection i
think this second one is more realistic
but i don't think it would kinda it
would boil down to the same
so i think that a society where there is
of course not universal
but overwhelming acceptance of
uh uh of logically defined property
rights
will still have a lot of margin for
conflict and political conflicts
and theory like uh yeah i'm i'm shooting
you but because you go you gave me
cancer and i mean you know think about
uh covered stuff okay uh i mean
you are not wearing a mask so you are
killing me
uh and then we have to argue about
actual uh probability of
oh i mean of course if i come to you
when i shoot you with a gun
i'm i'm basically trespassing your
school
if i if i have a gun with uh i'm playing
russia roulette
i have one bullet in a revolver of six
places and i shoot
i'm basically trespassing with one sixth
of probability
which is probably still enough for you
to try to to
to kill me in response but if i have
uh one uh one millions of guns with just
one bullet then the probability is
basically
is getting closer to probably driving
the car
and risking that i can have a seizure
while i drive and so i will kill you
and so you you should be able to kill me
whenever i drive a car
so the more complex this and then you go
to
the flu because i can kill you with the
flu or with the with the cold
it's unlikely but possible and i can
kill you with coronavirus and
and and sarskoff do of course so
uh the more complex the situation the
more you open again even
if everybody almost everybody accepts
the framework that we were discussing
there's still
room for conflict and political
disagreement
i disagree that it would be the same as
today
today the the the first modern
uh ethical relativism we and and
collectivist
uh mythology we are in is something that
allows complete craziness like
uh incredible claims
like uh for the color of your skin
i'm going to kill you uh which is not
the same
as having room for some kind of very
very far-fetched
complex uh claims of cause and effect
inside a rational framework so i
so i get your point it's not the end
it's not the end of history it's not the
end of conflicts
but i think it will be more local
conflicts for example
in a property rights setup uh the debate
about
the defense that we have will mostly be
about defense
you will have to prove that the seed
they planted by the fans but my father
uh he basically stopped the wind from
flowing and so
he didn't allow your seed to move and
but
it's ambiguous there can be mistakes
that can be abuses
but and we will probably need a jury of
our peers to judge some kind of third
party
uh so we will probably need bigger
organizations
in order to solve this kind of conflicts
i agree with you
but it's still different from the
current kind of
prevalent ethical relativism or
collectivism
in which the point is uh not about
defense anymore
the one who decides what defense must be
is the uh politicians politicians
in washington dc because of democracy
this is complete
giacomo i think that you wildly
misunderstand
how a lot of people you would call
postmodernist
ethical relativists actually see this
they don't see that as just
relative to whatever their
extending those time horizons
backwards and forwards
and if you really think about humanity
in our entire history it has been a long
story of us constantly trying to
lengthen in
way more ways than just thinking about
rights the time
horizons that we think in and concern
ourselves with
like that i would argue is a historical
trend
of this species through our whole
history
and so like the kind of like my entire
thinking
on this whole subject matter
is looking through that lens who really
cares what the definition of a right is
or where it is or the logical
construction of it
what can you actually accomplish enforce
and maintain for yourself
in the real world everything else is
utterly irrelevant to me when i look and
think
in that dynamic of defining rights and
that variable of time
and just how that has played out in
history
well for me
uh yeah like i think that plebs
will always be like on a totally
different level and thinking
about things in totally different ways
and always trying to look for
someone to like blame and for their own
issues whatever they are uh i do
understand
i think i understand your point shinobi
that yeah this is not maybe
like the most practical thing for the
whole world to use or to
like adopt these kind of rights or
standards or principles or whatever
but i for at least for me this is just
mainly like
i love these kind of discussions because
it's interesting to
hear and see like how far uh have people
like thought about in these different
ways of
like yeah doing things uh just
like mainly on just a theoretical
level like how sound is the logic
i think that's interesting maybe it's
not practical maybe it's practical for
just one percent of the people maybe
more maybe less
but i don't think that really matters
well i think it's perfectly practical i
don't think it's achievable
as a consensus but that's different like
i think that not having cancer
is healthy and and it works better than
having cancer
but if you have cancer that just not
achievable
acival because the better state is not
reachable right now because you are in a
[__] up situation
so i think that this is completely
scalable and rational and consistent and
also practical
but it's not practical to implement it
because we are in a pathological
situation
but getting back to shinobi's point i
think i understand it better
so is saying it's not just like people
are not
thinking in terms of objective rights
some of them are not
or not consistently anyway but most of
them are
just thinking about property rights
extending these
to some kind of higher kind of uh uh
of of systems you shinobi you're
stressing time
as a variable i probably would stress
more in symbols
because it's not really the point about
what i did a lot of times
of time ago it's more a point about what
other i mean most of the people today
are science uh stuff like
rights and compensation and
and restitutions and retribution
and ethical standards like these are on
top of
not individuals like i'm doing not
single human beings but some kind of
ensembles of
individuals like uh classes uh economic
classes or
races or uh real quick
i think that's a result of the time
horizon like you know what i mean
they're expanding it
to an ensemble or a group because when
you extend that time
horizon it's it's too difficult to
individually assign blame because blame
is
proportional instead of a discrete thing
on an individual
i completely agree this is a very good
point and
i think that uh the difference between
like me
and most of these people is that i
consider i have a discrete threshold
uh between methodology methodological
individualism
and and everything else which i would
call collectivism
so i completely agree with you once you
accept
to assign rights not to
single people doing actions but to
groups for whatever reason
then there is basically a slippery
slopes that can
bring on neko food to any kind of
ethical theory from
but then i think in order to accept that
i think that's true
but then there is no real difference
within this framework
between the typical liberal democrat of
today
and they committed nazi of the 30s they
are just
a slightly different uh application of
the same
basic framework which is collectivism so
the rights of some kind of example
can overcome the rights of an individual
and when you accept that
uh if the if the rights of the ensemble
are democracy
then it's okay to to shot a lady
entering
uh the capital uh palace because
she was against democracy and then you
can bomb people
in the middle east and you can do a lot
of [__] because it's just
against the the higher collective
concept
uh so i think that the real is not
really i mean you're right
that there is a continuity there is a
spectrum but within the spectrum
there is also a discrete threshold which
is
uh are you only counting individuals
or are you assuming the ethical
existence
of groups as ethical objects
and when you when you say that you
accept groups of
ethical objects then i think it's just a
matter of continuous
moving around these this uh time related
frame but when you stay in
methodological individualism
then even long-term scenarios like
inheritance
they become super complex but the
framework is very clear
did my father gave this stuff to me and
was it
justly acquired or not maybe we will
never be able to respond
out of complexity but the theoretical
question is very very
critical clear
and this is also the first discussion
between me and shinobi in which i don't
call him a communist basically so
good job you know this is the things
that
i really like about bitcoiners and even
about like
the old austrians that they were
actually able to have these like
reasonable discussions about different
opinions and not just throwing [__] at
each other well we also [__] each
other
for example if you do this on twitter
there is not enough bandwidth
to to use this kind of uh of nuances and
so we just uh we just
uh insult each other and that's all yeah
but that's okay
that's understandable uh by the way i
just
uh wanted to also hear giacomo like what
are your thoughts
if you have any insights about a
situation like for example
let's say that i acquire a proper
property
for like buy homesteading or
buying it from someone else like in this
austrian perspective
or like this moral perspective
um if i for example go for
a work trip or something like that for
let's say a week or maybe like for half
a year
a year 10 years when does this old
property of mine become
or again homesteadable
i don't think there's like a answer but
yeah just your thoughts
uh super difficult i don't think there
is a this is basically
in 18 laws and in most
most customary
um customary uh setups it was a
case-by-case situation and you have to
prove i mean you as a new amsteader had
to prove well actually
you just rhyme static because you think
it's free
and then the old owner will come back
and he will claim that you trespassed
and then a conflict will rise and then
uh
you in order to punish him
proportionally or to try them to punish
in proportion in order to be compensated
you will have to prove that he
trespasses
and so that it's still your property and
he will have to argue that it's not
and usually in customary rights there
was the concept of
abandoned property so a property in
which the original
appropriator could not or didn't want to
uh keep using it and and the burden of
the proof
is usually on the new occupant and
and this case by the case there there is
not a single
generalized response uh if you think
about that
it also goes in many bioethical stuff
like uh
uh like uh organ expand or or stuff like
that like
if you are dead and you don't have hairs
and you are
long decomposed then i probably can use
your stuff if i need it because you're
i mean you're not there anymore but if
you are sleeping
i cannot take your kidney because it's
true that you are not there to debate
with me
that that you that you would use your
kidney but it's it's a reasonable
assumption that
when you sleep i will not take your
kidney so uh
the point is in between uh where's the
threshold
uh are you in a reversible comma
uh it's a burden of the proof to to say
that it's really
uh are irreversible and there's a lot of
[__] going on in the middle so i would
say caseback is but
mostly like even in uh
in case like uh yeah
yeah somebody says that that man can
verify they didn't give you the
exact or they can but they cannot
communicate it to you uh depending on
your
afterlife uh theory so uh
so it's it's messy the same is a age
of uh age of uh maturity in order to
have property
uh underage people can they have
property
17 years old guy probably can um state
staff while saying that
a one years old baby has the right
to put his fingers inside the
electricity plug
because of of self-ownership
is probably more problematic so you have
to
you have to put you have a abandoned
stuff
is a problem to be decided case by case
and the claim that you have to do is
very clear
so there is no doubt in which kind of
claim you have to do your claim must be
the guy who appropriated could not or
didn't want to keep using it at the time
i reappropriated
uh so the claim is clear the application
of the claim
to a single specific situation is not
universal and i don't think you can say
three years or seven years it really
depends and you will need a conflict
resolution mechanism
in order to uh to prove and counter
proof
same goes for age or mental health like
i can i can i can take these guys to the
hospital because it's just crazy and so
is
is suicidal but in a crazy way so i had
to stop him
coercing him can i or can't i in some
cases it's obvious like
some case of all of alzheimer's syndrome
is super obvious in with small babies is
super obvious
with like 17 years old kids
uh it's not very obvious with with the
guy with
a very soft
alzheimer uh situation is not at all
obvious
so uh i think that again fiat
laws where you i i one i think that i
know for certain
then electing a politician
based on how much consensus can he buy
in exchange for free lunch in order to
go
to a [__] town uh miles away from the
conflict
in order to write down a magical number
which is the magical amount of years
that have to pass in order to uh to have
a abandoned
staff or age of consent or age of
alcohol or driving or whatever i know
that this will be
always sub-optimal to any other kind of
local consensus
discovery mechanism which is the the
right consensus
depends case-by-case i'll actually give
uh
an example of uh how this works today
there's a
community in denmark called chilean this
is basically a hippie town that was
established after a festival there in
the 70s and the way
it works there in in their communities
basically you can homestead
in the area there you can just go there
and the only thing you need you need
approval of
all your neighbors so if your neighbors
approve of you
they allow you to build a new house
there and homestead so that's the way
they they do it there
hmm that's an interesting idea and they
actually have
they have like wikipedia says it's a
micronation with its own
territory and they actually have uh
special rights in denmark in terms of uh
building regulations and and some other
things so it's
it's a very interesting thing and
there's actually some people who live
there
which are planning on moving to
liberstad instead because they have some
issues with
a consensus-based governance in in the
town but it's still
like there's a lot of things you could
learn from this because this has been
going on since the 70s
and the adults there today are children
that grew up from the parents uh
establishing there
i'll share the link
so you're not talking about oh you're
not talking about it it seems very close
to christiania
as a as no i wouldn't say
it's in i don't know it that much in
detail
but it's more like a community where
people actually staying and living
and enjoying life together creating
music
and stuff and it's a very different area
compared to
castiano
right well one of the things that i
would like to make clear
is that the fact that i think that that
property riots
can be rationally defined as objective
that of of course at least in theory
then you have to discover them
in practice which is more complex and
they can be
and should be defended in in theory uh
doesn't mean that i expect them to be
recognized by
fiat jurisdiction at all so
my my claim is not that since this this
is right
then people will allow us to do this
uh i think this is completely naive and
that would be my
my main concern with the operations like
i don't know i i don't know if you guys
have seen the movie about the island of
the roses in italy
it was a very nice story i was following
the story already when i was a kid when
i was 16 year olds
and now there is a net netflix movie and
it's
kind of almost uh trustworthy to the
to the original story and uh this guy
just created a
system platform in the next to remini
and uh and the movie doesn't show it but
it started also to
sell fuel for for for boats
without taxes and also there was a
restaurant and a bar
without taxes and uh so it was there was
also a tax implication
and also there was uh sexual laws
implication
like uh that there were stricter uh laws
about uh
sexual behavior back then so there was a
bunch of stuff with legal implication
and then the the even if it was outside
the
the national waters uh the italian
government
just sent the ship to to to sink it down
with missiles
and and then with dynamites because
missiles didn't work
and so my point is i don't expect
uh nation states which are not based
on even in a anymore a
a pretence of objective rights anymore
uh to respect any of these so i think
that
the question the question of what is
right is mostly useful to understand how
to
constrain yourself in order to not do
something that you consider
wrong so i will not uh kill
this guy or steal this stuff or rape
this girl
because it is wrong and i wish i will
not do that because it is wrong
but uh it doesn't mean that i expect
people around me
not to do it because it's wrong so i
have to build the
tools and strategies to prevent people
from doing it because most of the people
will try to do it
even if i prove logically that is wrong
they will still try to do it
so i will not not only will not rely
on objective rights to protect me i will
not
even uh i will not even
talk too much i mean personally i do
because i'm because i'm
stupid but i will not suggest people to
be super
overt about the right that they have
but mean but they i would suggest them
to be more sneaky and to just
claim stuff by doing and building tools
and using tools
let's say like this uh i
i talk about bitcoin a lot but what is
smart is just
shutting up about bitcoin and protecting
it and avoiding kyc and mixing it and
keep it safe uh in a good course storage
not talking about them so the fact that
rights are
universal and objective doesn't mean
that you should spend your life
claiming rights expecting other people
especially now
to follow them because uh any kind of
pretense of respect of universal
laws uh is completely gone since the
i i would say since the 80s or the or
the 70s
uh probably after world war two there
was a little bit of
pretense of of of objective
uh just naturalistic human rights
definition but now there is not anymore
and especially in 20 in 2020 and 2021
every i mean everything the governments
are doing is not just immoral it's
already aware
but it's also strictly speaking legal
and nobody just cares i mean
constitutions are completely overcome
there is no way you can appeal to the
constitution to defend yourself
it's it's it's absolutely it's toilet
paper uh
it's really where was in theory but now
it's treated as such
by every single law in every single
country i can say
and exceptions i don't think they are
relevant as sustainable
so i would rather go with an agorist
approach like
you have this right but don't just claim
it
speaking you have to claim it by
building and using
weapons and tools to take it
hmm okay
yeah giacomo i think you would be a good
uh
judge on this private company
like private legal company of the
citadel
great i have a job for the future
you're going to get the competition
though that's important to have
different
institutions of law that can
people can subscribe to and have
agreements with
yeah and also in when you want to
when you need decentralization as a not
as a principle
but as a tool to to to resist
to uh powerful adversaries
then you have to restrain yourself i
mean even if i was
even if you create the perfect community
probably you want to break it up
down to two different competing
communities you want to keep it small
basically
because even if you can legitimately
build something big
the chances for you to be either
attacked
or corrupted when you become big
are very very uh are are very very high
like i think this is the problem with
the typical iranian
idea of uh super huge businessman and
entrepreneur like
you know the end rain hero so the jungle
the problem with the jungle is that if
you don't stop
before becoming super successful uh
from the economic point of view uh uh
you are either attacked and and just uh
put away easily like ross wulbrick
or you become corrupted like i mean
there are many libertarian
successful entrepreneurs that become
statist
the second they started to be able to
use the government
for their own interest but i don't even
blame them too much because it's obvious
i mean you may be i mean peter thiel is
a great libertarian thinker
that by the first second he had the
power to the
the opportunity to use government
violence to
uh to steal other people's property out
of uh
something uh out of the problem of uh
reputation attacks so acting outside
property rights
he did and uh and the same goes for
basically everybody i mean
i don't elon musk is a good guy
but he's too big to stay
consistent with principle uh and
eventually the maybe maybe zuckenberg
started off as a communist bastard
but even if you don't start off like
that
when you are very very big you end up
like that this is not a problem of uh
of legitimacy it is legitimate to become
jeff bezos it's just unlikely that you
can stan
you can stay principled when you become
one
so even when you build business and
stuff
i think that there is a new awareness
among bitcoiners
due to the fact that we know what
central is what decentralization is
uh there is this kind of self-censorship
in which
a good one in which we say okay i have
to
i have to skate up so i try to
explain better what i think with this
example
let's assume you create a a an exchange
and and then you say i really want
everybody on this planet to use my
exchange bitcoin exchange and then you
say oh [__] no this is a nightmare
because
then i become a single point of failure
i do want uh to have at least
five or six good competitors same goes
if you produce an outdoor wallet
i mean if you talk with uh with nikola
or
or or rodolfo uh if they
seriously imagine the situation in which
everybody uses
a nano x or or a call card uh that's a
they they should be able to acknowledge
that's a very bad scenario
because they become a single point of
failure so uh
with respect to the uh pro market
entrepreneurs of the past
bitcoiners have this kind of added
awareness
not only i should not aggress
other people but i should not become
a single point of failure that will
be brought easily to do that eventually
yeah i think that's a good point i mean
the same dynamics
plays out with for example in mining
like whenever someone
some pool gets way too much of power and
control people are starting to like
avoid it and
yeah they will like it might not be even
good for a mining pool to try to
uh achieve that big of a like majority
uh in the market for themselves so
yeah yeah
yeah i remember a lot of discussion with
the donations for development when we
had
all that the bad debacle and and and
drama about the be foundation
so i was asking for donation to give it
to open source development projects
i was doing that with bhb network and
adam beck was doing the same
with the with some of the block stream
uh budget
and then elena was doing the same with
the satoshi labs people
and everybody was doing kind of the same
and so we discussed it and we said oh
this is very inefficient
let's be more efficient let's centralize
let's create
one thing that can be that can be
interfaced with huge companies that
maybe can write off donations as tax
exempt
so we can drive a lot of money very
efficiently to bitcoin development
then we went on a stage in riga and we
were
very happy because i mean there was uh
well panda
and adam back and slash a lot of good
people
and james lop and francis puyata
very well intentioned people uh
and and we didn't even expect to be so
many
uh it was very spontaneous but then i
started to joke about the bitcoin
foundation and gavin anderson
and i was it was obvious to me it was a
joke
but then in the next days i understood
that people were
generally concerned and rightly so
because what we created
was something potentially efficient but
also
super easy to target single point of
failure
and so basically we we well we basically
dismantled it
and and critics were right i
some of the people on the stage with me
didn't understood
didn't understand the the criticism they
thought it was like personal
or or questioning the good faith but it
was not that it was not questioning the
good faith it was
questioning the fact that it was too
many
too much famous people on the same stage
asking for money to con to uh to
contribute to the development
right now like we have seen we had this
this mythology of block stream
conspiracy theories
and and i mean most people in blockchain
some people in blockchain understood
that there was
a real problem even if there was not a
real conspiracy
inside block stream and the same goes
with uh
with the chain collapse of course and
now with bring
i mean there is there is risk
if if if tumor i mean if uh in one year
uh newberry is the new one reason
we have a single point of failure which
is completely unrelated
with the good faith or or the good
intentions
of one guy or the other so
yeah we have the same and i personally
have seen the same with
the bee situation
yeah i remember when you guys were
talking about it on the
puddle huddle
but yeah interesting
[Music]
yeah it was a [__] show after that there
was a i i
actually loved it because it was it was
funny
somebody created the e foundation uh
to to market with ethereum and somebody
the bs foundation so the [__]
foundation
and somebody and rondolfonova came up
with the hats
anti-v foundation in like a few days and
i still have
like tense i i have a lot of hats
uh no nobody in my
in my home in switzerland and it was it
was funny a very good
uh immune reaction i have to say
yep
does anyone has any thoughts or
questions or other topics in mind
i was just thinking that now we have
been on this call for
four and a half hours half hour
i think we have a stream for three hours
and yeah
yeah i think it's it may it may be
enough
all right yeah i will end the stream and
yeah thanks for everyone who's
watching uh thanks for everyone who
participated on
in this call and yeah
i'll just shut the stream just a sec
just a second great